<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The city of Londons rejoinder to Mr. Attorney General's replication in the Quo warranto brought by him against their charter wherein they plead, that, I. By prescription they have a right, 1. To appoint, alter, and change rhc [sic] markets within the city from one place to another, 2. To regulate markets and</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 135 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A33194</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12950755</idno>
  <idno type="VID">95896</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240921986</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing C4361</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R15338</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">12950755</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A33194)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 95896)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 733:41)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The city of Londons rejoinder to Mr. Attorney General's replication in the Quo warranto brought by him against their charter wherein they plead, that, I. By prescription they have a right, 1. To appoint, alter, and change rhc [sic] markets within the city from one place to another, 2. To regulate markets and</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Attorney-General (1681-1687 : Sawyer)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 35 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and are to be sold by L. Curtiss,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata: prelim. p. [2].</note>
                  <note>Latin and English in parallel columns.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="corporate_name">London (England). --  Charter.</term>
               <term type="corporate_name">City of London (England). --  Court of Common Council.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Popish Plot, 1678.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Markets --  England --  London.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">London (England) --  Charters, grants, privileges.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-02 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-02 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:95896:1"/>
            <p>THE City of Londons REJOINDER, TO Mr. Attorney General's REPLICATION <hi>In the Quo Warranto</hi> Brought by him against their CHARTER.</p>
            <p>Wherein they Plead, That I. By <hi>Prescriptiion</hi> they have a <hi>Right,</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>1. To appoint, alter, and change the <hi>Markets</hi> within the <hi>City</hi> from one place to another.</item>
                  <item>2. To regulate <hi>Markets</hi> and to ascertain <hi>Tolls</hi> and <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sages,</hi> which were Levied as well upon <hi>Freemen</hi> as <hi>Ʋn-Freemen.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>They also Plead, II. That upon serious Consideration had of the Proceedings of the late <hi>Damnable Propish-Plot</hi> by them mentioned for the destruction of the <hi>KINGS</hi> most sacred Person, the Extirpation of the <hi>Protestant Religion,</hi> and the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>version of the <hi>Civil-Government,</hi> The <hi>Common Council</hi> out of their great Zeal and Loyalty to the King, agreed to the <hi>Petition</hi> incerted in Mr. <hi>Attorney-General's</hi> said <hi>REPLICATION.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed, And are to be sold by <hi>L. Curtiss.</hi> 1682.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:95896:2"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>THE Reader is desired instead of <hi>ad Parliamen'</hi> in the last Line of the 13 Page, to read <hi>ad Session' Parliamenti'</hi> and in the 2d. Line of the 14th Page, instead of <hi>Sexto</hi> to read <hi>Decimo Quinto:</hi> and in the 3d. Line of the same Page after the word <hi>Primo,</hi> to read <hi>ad Per Proro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gat' Tent'</hi> and to make the like amendments in the English. Literal and other small mistakes, it is hoped will be easily pardoned.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="rejoinder">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:95896:2"/>
            <head>THE CITY OF <hi>Londons Rejoinder,</hi>
            </head>
            <div xml:lang="lat" type="version">
               <head>Major &amp; Communitas ac Cives Civit' <hi>London,</hi> ad Sectam Dom' Regis.</head>
               <p>ET predict. Major &amp; Comunitas ac Cives Civitatis <hi>London</hi> quoad predict. placit. predicti At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tornat. dicti Domini Regis nunc Generalis in Assign. foris factur, Libertat. Privileg. &amp; Franches. sequen. videlt. ipsos Majorem &amp; Comunitat. ac Cives Civitatis <hi>London</hi> fore de seipsos unum Corpus Corporat. &amp; politicum in re facto &amp; nomine per nomen Majoris &amp; Comunitatis ac Civium Civitatis <hi>London</hi> ac per idem nomen placitare &amp; implicitari responde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re ac responderi per ipsos superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us clamat. superius replicando pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citat. protestando qund placit. illud ac materia in eodem content. minus sufficien. in Lege existunt ad ipsos Majorem &amp; Comunitatem ac Cives Civitatis <hi>London</hi> de Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertat. Privileg. &amp; Franches. il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis abjudicand. sive exclud<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd. protestando etiam quod null is actus vel factum neque aliqua or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinatio Anglice <hi>By-Law</hi> per Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mune Concilium vel per Majorem Aldermanos &amp; Commune Conci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium Civitatis predict. confect. est Actus vel factum Corporis Corporat. &amp; Politici predict. pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testando{que} etiam quod ipsi predict. Major. &amp; Comunitas ac Cives Civitat. <hi>London</hi> contra fiduciam
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:95896:3"/>in eis reposit. nunquam assumpser. super se aliquam illicitam vel in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>justant potestatem ad deuar. de subditis &amp; ligeis Domini Regis Levand. ad privat. Lucrum &amp; commodum ipsor. Majoris &amp; Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unitat. ac Civium Civitat. <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> colore Legum sive ordinatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num per ipsos fact. sive ordinat. prout predict. Attorn. dicti Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni Regis nunc Generalis pro eo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem Domino Rege superius suppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition. protestando{que} ulterius quod iidem. Major &amp;. Comunitas ac Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ves Civitatis <hi>London</hi> non Leva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. seu exeger. tantas denar. summas per Annum de personis ad publica Marcata infra Civitat. predict. tent. cum Victualibus &amp; Provisionibus ibidem Venden. ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceden. quant. dictus At torn. Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neralis pro eodem Domino Rege superius allegavit pro placito ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men quoad confection. &amp; publica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Legis pro Levatione denari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or. de personis ad publica Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cata infra Civitat. predict. tent. cum Victualibus &amp; Provisionibus ibidem venden. acceden. ac exacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem &amp; Levation. hujusmodi de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nar. supertus fieri supposit. iidem Major. &amp; Comunitas ac Cives Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitat. <hi>London</hi> dicunt quod Civitas <hi>London</hi> predict est &amp; a tempore cujus contrarij memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria hominum non existit fuit summa &amp; Capitalis Civitas &amp; Metropolis ac principalis Portus hujus Regni Anglie &amp; in Civibus &amp; Inhabitantibus maxime populo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sa &amp; in concursu hominum tam Ligeor. Domini Regis quam ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traneor. copiosissima Emporium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que totius <hi>Europe</hi> celeberrimum Quodque habentur &amp; tenentur &amp; a tempore cujus contrarij me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moria Hominum non existunt
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:95896:3"/>hal ebantur &amp; tenebantur publica Mercata infra Civitat' praed' pro victualibus, pro provisionibus, &amp; al' bonis &amp; Merchandis adinde ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct' thidem vendend' Quodque ipsi prad' Maior &amp; Communitas ac Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ves Civitat' London' praed' docimo septimo die Septembris Anno vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesimo sexto supradicto in replica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione praedict' mentionat' necnon continue postea, &amp; à tempore cujus contrarii memoria Hominum non existit seizit' fuer' &amp; adhuc seizit' existunt de &amp; in publicis Mercatis praed' in Dimesn' suo, ut de Feodo, ac per totum idem tempus sumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus suis propriis provider' ac pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>videre consuever' &amp; debuerunt Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra Mercatoria sive Loca ubi hujus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modi Mercata tent' fuer' quoties<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunqe necesse fuit, &amp; Stallas, Stationes, &amp; al' Accommodationes pro personis ad eadem. Mercata ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nien' cum victualibus &amp; provisioni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus ibidem vendend' pro meliori &amp; magis convenien' venditioni exposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione eorundem, &amp; Supervisores &amp; alios Officiarios Mercatorum illorum pro preservatione boni Ordinis in eisdem Mercatis, &amp; meliori regula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione eorundem, &amp; magni concursus populi adinde confluen' ac emunda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verunt &amp; emundare consueverunt, &amp; debuerunt Fora Mercatoria prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicta, &amp; pro sustentatione dictorum sumptuum suorum per totum tempus praedictum habuer' &amp; perceper' ac habere &amp; percipere consuever' di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versas rationabiles Toluet' Ratas, sive denariorum summas de quibus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunque personis ad Mercata praed. sic ut praesertur venien' pro Stallis,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:95896:4"/>Stationibus, &amp; aliis Accommoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionibus per eas pro venditioni expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitione hujusmodi victualium &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>visionum in Mercat is illis habit. Et iidem Major &amp; Communitas ac Cives Civitat' London' ulterius di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunt, quod Cives &amp; Liberi homines Civitatis praed' praedicto decimo septimo die Septembris, Anno vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesimo sexto supradicto, &amp; semper fuer', &amp; adhuc existu<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> alde nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merosi, videlicet, q<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>ta mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le homines &amp; plur<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>dque in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fra dictam' Civi<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> videli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cet, apud praed' Parochiam Sancti Michaelis Bassiesha<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> in Warda de Bassieshaw, à tempore cujus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarii memoria hominum non existit habebatur, &amp; fuit Commune Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilium ejusdem Civitatis de tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore in tempus, quoties necesse fuit, in eadem Civitate assemblat', con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistens de Majore &amp; Alderm' dicte Civitatis pro tempore existen' ac de quibusdam Civibus existen' Liberis hominibus Civitatis illius, non ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceden' numerum ducentar' &amp; quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaginta personarum è Civibus &amp; Liberis hominibus Civitat' praed' annuatim Elect' fore de Communi Concilio, illo, qui quidem Cives sic Elect' in hujusmodi Communi Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilio vo cantur Communiarii, Ang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, <hi>Commons.</hi> Civitat' London' Quodque infra Civitat' praed' vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licet apud praed. Parochiam Sancti Michaelis Bassieshaw, in Warda de Bassieshaw praed. habetur, &amp; existit, &amp; à tempore cujus contrarii memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria hominum non existit habebatur, &amp; suit talis consuetudo usitat' &amp; ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probat' videlicet quod Major &amp; Alderm' dict' Civit' ac hujusmodi Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ves sic Elect' fore de Com' Conc'ejusdem
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:95896:4"/>Civitatis pro tempore existen' in Communi Concilio suo infra Civitat' ibid, assemblat' à toto tempore su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pradicto secundum consuetudinem Civitat' praed' fecer' &amp; constituer' ac facere &amp; constituere consuever' &amp; possunt ac potuer' Leges &amp; Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinationes pro meliori Regulatione &amp; Gubernatione publicor' Mercator' infra Civitat' praed. ac pro ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>punctuatione convenien' Locor' &amp; Tempor' quando &amp; ubi infra ean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem Civitat' Mercata. illa. tent' fiunt, &amp; pro assessione, &amp; in rectitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinem reductione rationabilium To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luet', Ratar' sive denar' summarum solvend' per personas ad eadem Mercata venien' pro Stallis, Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionibus, &amp; aliis Accommodationi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus per eas pro venditioni exposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione victualium &amp; provisionum in Mercatis illis habit' quoties, &amp; quando eis videbitur expediri, dum tamen Leges &amp; Ordinationes hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jusmodi Domino Regi &amp; populo suo sint utiles, &amp; bonae Fidei &amp; Ratione consone, ac Legibus &amp; Statut' hujus Reg. Anglie minime contrar' Quod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que in magna Carta de Libertati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus Anglie in Parliamento Dom' Henrici quondam Regis Anglie Tertii apud Westm' in Com' Middle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sex, An. Regni sui nono tent' edit' &amp; provis' continetur quod Civitas Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don' habeat omnes Libertates suas Antiquas &amp; Consuetudines suas; &amp; iidem Major &amp; Communitas ac Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ves Civitat' London' ulterius dicunt, quod Dominus Edwardus quondam Rex Anglie tertius in Parliamento suo apud Westmon' in Com' Midd.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:95896:5"/>Anno Regni sui primo tent' per quandam Cartam suam de assensu Praelator' Comitum Baronum ac totius Communitatis Regni sui in codem Parliamento suo apud Westm' praed' convocat' existen' ac autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritate ejusdem Parliamenti con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmavit tunc Civibus Civitat' London' praed' Libertates subse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quen' (inter alia) habend' sibi &amp; Successoribus suis in perpet' imprimis recitando, Quod cum in magna Carta de Libertatibus An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glie contineatur quod Civitas Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don habeat omnes Libertates suas antiquas &amp; Consuetudines suas, &amp; quod iidem Cives tempore confectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis dict' Carte, ac temporibus St. Edwardi Regis, &amp; Confessoris, &amp; Will' Conquestoris, &amp; al' Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genitor' dicti Regis Edwardi Tertii, diversas Libertates &amp; Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suetudines tam per Cartas ipsorum Progenitorum suorum quam sine Cartis, ex Antiqua Consuetudine ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buissent voluit; &amp; concessit idem Rex Edwardus tertius pro se &amp; Heredibus suis per Cartam ill' au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritate praed' quod iidem Cives haberent Libertates suas secundum Formam magne Carte supradict' prout per eandem Cartam geren' Dat apud Westm. praed' sexto die Martii, Anno Regni Domini Regis Edwardi Tertii primo supradicto, sub magno Sigillo suo Anglie Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gillat' hic in Cur' prolat' inter alia plenius apparet. Et iidem Major, &amp; Civitas, ac Cives Civitat' Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don' uiterius dicunt, Quod ad instant'
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:95896:5"/>London' seu per nomen Civium-Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>&amp; requisitionem Communitatis Reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni Anglie in Parliamento Domini Richardi nuper Regis Anglie se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundi post Conq' apud Westm' praed. Anno Regni sui septimo tent' assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blat' pro majori quiete &amp; pace in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Ligeos ejusdem nuper Regis fovend. &amp; pro bono publico, omnes Consuetudines, Libertates, Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leg' &amp; Franchises Civitat. praed. tunc Civibus Civitat. praed &amp; co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Successoribus, Authoritate ejus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem Parliamenti ratificat' &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmat' fuer' Quodque praedictus Dominus Rex nunc per Literas suas Patentes sub magno Sigillo suo Anglie Sigillat. geren. Dat. apud Westm. praed. vicesimo quarto die Junii, Anno Regni sui decimo quinto. quas iidem Major &amp; Communitas, ac Cives Civitat. London. hic in Cur' proferunt, pro ipso Rege Hered. &amp; Successoribus suis ratificavit &amp; confirmavit Majori &amp; Communitati ac Civibus Civitat. London. &amp; Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessoribus suis omnia &amp; singula, ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risdictiones, Authoritat. Privileg. Libertates, Franchises, Quietantias, Immunitates, &amp; Consuetudines que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunque que praefat. Major &amp; Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munitas, ac Cives Civitat. London. vel Praedecessores sui per nomen Majoris &amp; Communitat. ac Civium Civitat. London. seu per nomen Majoris, Alderm. Civium' &amp; Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitat. London. seu per nomen Majoris &amp; Civium Civitat' Lond. seu per no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men Majoris &amp; Communitat. Civitat.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:95896:6"/>vitatis London' seu per nomen Baron London' seu per nomen Baron Civitat. Lendon' seu per aliquod aliud nomen quodcunque ratione vel vigore Literar' Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentium, Cartar' seu confirmation' in e<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>sdem Literis Patentibus dicti Domini Regis prementionat' vel alicujus seu aliquor' usus vel usuum, Prescriptionis vel Prescriptionum seu alio Legali modo quocunque aliquo tempore, vel aliquibus tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poribus ante tunc habuissent, seu rationabilit. usi fuissent aut exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuissent, habend. tenend. gaudend. &amp; exercend. omnia &amp; singula premissa praed. eisdem Majori &amp; Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tati, ac Civibus Civitat. London. Praed. &amp; Successoribus suis imperpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuum adeo plene libere &amp; integre, ac in tam amplis modo &amp; forma prout in iisdem Literis Patentibus superius mentionantur fore data, sive concessa, aut aliter usu, Prescript' vel alio Legali modo, seu jure quocun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que ante tunc respective habit' ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent' sive gavisa fuissent, ac si se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratim, singulatim &amp; nominatim in &amp; per dictas Literas Patentes ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sius Domini Regis nunc express. nominat. declarat. concessa &amp; mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>festa essent &amp; fuissent, prout per easdem Literas Patentes (inter alia) plenius apparet. Et iidem Major &amp; Communitas ac Cives Civitat. London. ulterius dicunt, quod post magnam illam Conflagra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion' maxime partis Civitat. Praed. quae fuit in mense Septembris, Anno Dom. Millesimo sexcentesimo sexa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gesimo sexto ac alteration' in Civit' &amp; Mercat' praed. perinde occasionat'
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:95896:6"/>diverse controversie &amp; questiones orte fuer' infra eandem Civitat' de &amp; concernen' Stabilition' Merca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor' &amp; dendr' summar' per Ligeos Dom. Regis pro victualibus &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>visionibus in Mercatis illis venditio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni exposit' solubil' ac superinde praed. die Jovis decimo septimo die Septembris, Anno Regni dicti Dom. Regis nunc vicesimo sexto supradicto, quidam Will. Hooker Miles, tunc Major Civitat' praed. &amp; Alderm' dicte Civitat' ac Communiarii sive Cives de Communi Concilio ejusdem Civitatis tunc existen' in Communi Concilio suo infra candem Civitat' (scil. in praed. Camera Guildhall Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitatis illius, scituat' in praed. Paro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chia Sancti Michaelis Bassieshaw in Warda de Bassieshaw praed. (ad tunc assemblat' secundum Consuetudinem dicte Civitat' ac Authoritate ejusdem Communis Concilii secer' constituer' &amp; publicaver quendam Actum sive Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination' pro meliori regulatione &amp; gubernatione publicorum Mercator. infra Civitat' praed. tent' intitulat' <hi>An Act for the settlement and well ordering of the several publick Markets within the City of</hi> Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don. Per quem quidem Actum sive Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination inter alia recitando, quod cum pro accommodation' popult Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat. Anglice <hi>of Market people,</hi> cum Stallis, asseribus, tectur' Anglice <hi>shel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> &amp; aliis hujusmodi rebus necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riis pro eor' Stationibus in aliquibus Mercat' infra Civitat' ill ac pro emundand' paviend' escurand' &amp; mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da custodiend' eadem; Ac etiam pro sustinendo, Anglice <hi>defraying,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciden' onera reparationis &amp; manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentionis dictorum Mercator' &amp; scilicet ad gratificand' &amp; munerand' curam &amp; attendentiam talium perso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narum qual. forent occupat' in eis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem quaedam rationabiles Rate pro dict. accommodationibus &amp; oneribus, semper solut, fuissent &amp; ad inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:95896:7"/>quod dicte Rate forent certe &amp; publice facte omni populo Merca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torio, Anglice <hi>Market-people,</hi> per quod persone que extunc per ordinem illius Cur' Com. Concilii occupat' forent tanquam Collectores, vel Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptores carundem Ratar' preveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentur à demandando, exigendo, seu recipiendo plus quam allocat. fuit per Actum sive Ordination. ill' ordinat. &amp; inactitat. fuit Authoritate ejus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem Com. Concilii inter alia, quod omnes &amp; quelibet persona &amp; persone ad aliquod dict. Mercator. accedend. ad commoditates suas vendend. &amp; uttand. extunc solverent tali persone seu personis quales fuer. vel forent de tempore in tempus appun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuat. ad capiend. &amp; recipiend. pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficua omnium vel aliquor. dictor. Mercator. ad usum Majoris &amp; Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munitatis ac Civium Civitat. Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don. de &amp; ab omni populo Mercatorio adinde acceden. pro Stallis, Stationi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, &amp; aliis accommodationibus suis in separal. Mercatis praed. ut prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fertur, secundum Ratas sequen. &amp; non amplius; videl. pro qualibet Stalla sive Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. de Longitudine octo pedum &amp; Latitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine quatuor pedum pro venditione carnis; aut piscis duos solid. &amp; sex denar. per sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tim. pro qualibet Stalla sive Statione de Longitudine sex pedum &amp; Latitudine quatuor pedum duos solid. per septiman. pro qualibet Stalla sive Statione de longitudine sex vel octo pedum &amp; latitudine quatuor pedum, &amp; aliis commoditatibus tres denar. per diem, pro quolibet onere equino provision. non super Stallas, vel sub publica tectur. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glice <hi>shelter,</hi> duos denar. per diem, pro qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libet Camistra, Anglice <hi>Dosser,</hi> consimilis pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vision' un' denar' per diem; pro qual' care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctat' tract. cum non plur. quam tribus Equis quatuor denar. per diem pro qual. carectat. tract. cum quat. Equis vel pluribus sex denar. per diem. Ac ulterius ordinat. &amp; inactitat. fuit dicta Authoritate quod Collectores aut Receptores appunctuat' vel appunctuand. ut prefertur, haberent potestatem super obsti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinata denegatione seu delatione alicujus populs Mercatorii, ad solvend. respectivas Ratas praedict. illos ab eorum respectivis Stationibus &amp; locis amovere &amp; dislocare.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:95896:7"/>Et iidem Maior &amp; Communitas ac Cives Civitat. <hi>London.</hi> ulterius di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunt quod eaedem ratae per Actum sive ordinationum ill. ut prefertur solvi ordinat. predict. tempore con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectionis ordinationis illius &amp; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunc hucusque fuerunt rationabiles &amp; adhuc rationabiles existunt quod que ratae &amp; denariorum summae per eundem Actum sive Ordinationem solvi ordinat. sunt omnes ratae to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luet. &amp; denarior. summae pro victu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alibus &amp; provisionibus in Mercat. predict. vendit. seu venditioni ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posit. per aliquas personas à dicto tempore confectionis ejusdem Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nationis hucusque ad usum Matoris &amp; Communitat. ac civum Civitat. <hi>London.</hi> solubil. &amp; solut. quas quidem ratas sic solvi ordinat. &amp; nuli. alias iidem Maior &amp; Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muntas ac cives Civitatis <hi>London.</hi> à tempore Actus sive ordinationis illius ut praefertur fact. hucusque ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eger. &amp; perceper. secundum formam &amp; effectum ejusdem Actus sive Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinationis. Qui quidem Actus sive Ordinatio est eadem Lex per ipsos Maiorem &amp; Communitat, ac cives Civitat. <hi>London.</hi> superius de facto inactitat. fore supponit. in predict. placito predict. Attorn. Generalis su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perius replicando placitat. spec. Abs{que} hoc quod aliqua Lex actus sive or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinatio pro levatione denar. predict. de personis ad Mercata predict. ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedend. cum Victualibus &amp; provisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onibus ibid. vendend. inactitat. sive fact. fuit aliter vel alio modo quam iidem Maior. &amp; Communitas ac ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ves Civitatis <hi>London.</hi> superius alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaver. prout idem Attorn. Generalis pro dicto Dom. Rege nunc superius suppon. &amp; hoc parat. sunt verisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>care:
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:95896:8"/>Et quoad resid. predict. pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citi predicti Attornat: Generalis in Assign. forisfactur. ut praefertur su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perius replicando placitat. iidem Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or &amp; Communitat. ac Cives Civi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tat. <hi>London.</hi> dicunt quod vicesimo quarto die <hi>Aprilis,</hi> Anno regni dict. Dom. Regis nunc tricesimo &amp; per diversos Annos tunc ult. elapsos ac post eundem vicesimum quartum di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>em <hi>Aprilis,</hi> infra hoc regnum <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliae</hi> &amp; alibi, videlicet apud <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don.</hi> predict. in predict. Parochia Sanct. <hi>Michaelis Bassishaw</hi> in War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da de <hi>Bassishaw</hi> predict. proditoria &amp; execrabilis conspiratio &amp; conju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratio machinat. &amp; prosecut. fuit per Papistas, Anglicè <hi>Papists,</hi> ad in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terficiend. &amp; murdrand. Dom. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gem nunc &amp; ad altercand. mutand. &amp; subvertend. antiquas gubernation. &amp; Leges ejusdem Regni &amp; ad sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>primend. veram Religionem in eo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem stabilit. &amp; ad extirpandum &amp; distruendum professores ejusdem Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligionis: Quae quidem conspiratio &amp; conjuratio machinat. &amp; prosecut. fuer. in diversis locis &amp; per separat. vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as &amp; media ac per magnum nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum personarum separat. qualitat. &amp; graduum quae agebant &amp; se oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupaver. in eisdem ad exequend. &amp; perimplend. predicta scelerata &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditoria machinationes &amp; proposita: Quodque postea, scilicet, Vicesimo septimo die <hi>Septembris</hi> Anno trice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>simo supradicto, <hi>Edmundus-Bury Godfrey</hi> Miles tunc unus Justiciar. Dom. Regis ad pacem in Comit. <hi>Middl.</hi> conservandum assignat. secun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum Officii &amp; juramenti sui debitum apud Parochiam Sancti <hi>Martini</hi> in Campis in eodem Comitat. <hi>Middl.</hi> cepit Examination. &amp; Information.
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:95896:8"/>de praefat. Conspiratione &amp; Conju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratione, ac Information. quod magna illa Conflagratio maximae partis Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitatis <hi>London.</hi> quae suisset in men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se <hi>Septembris</hi> Anno Dom. millimo sexcentesimo sexagesimo sexto fact. suit per Papistas, posteaque per ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>visamentum, assensum, consilium, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stigationem &amp; procurationem aliquo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum dictorum Conspiratorum diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sae personae in insidiis intuer. &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secut. fuerunt praefat. <hi>Edmundus-Bury Godfrey</hi> diversis diebus ea in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentione ad ipsum murdrand. vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licet apud Parochiam Sanct. <hi>Mariae le Savoy</hi> in dicto Comitat. <hi>Middl.</hi> Quod quidem murdrum postea, scil. duodecimo die <hi>Octobris</hi> Anno tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesimo supradicto, apud eandem Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rochiam per eos perpetrat. &amp; effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum fuit; ac perpetrat. &amp; factum fuit ea intentione ad supprimendum Examination. &amp; Information. quas ipse ut praefertur cepisset, &amp; ad de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrend. &amp; intimidand. Magistrat. &amp; al. ab agendo in ulteriori detectione Conspirationis &amp; Conjurationis pred. Pro quo quidem Murdro quidam <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertus Greene, <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                        <desc> _____ </desc>
                     </gap> Girald</hi> Clericus, <hi>Henricus Bury, Lauren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cius Hill, Dominic Kelley</hi> &amp; <hi>Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libertus Vernatt,</hi> postea, scilicet Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mino Sanct. <hi>Hillarii</hi> Annis Regni dict. Dom. Regis nunc tricesimo &amp; tricesimo primo in Curia Dom. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis coram ipso Rege apud <hi>Westm.</hi> in dicto Com. <hi>Middl.</hi> per quandam Juram. praedict. ejusdem Com. <hi>Middl.</hi> debita juris forma indictat. fuerunt. Ad quod quidem Indictamentum, postea, scilicet eodem Termino pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict. <hi>Robertus Green, Henricus Bury,</hi> &amp; <hi>Laurencius Hill,</hi> separatim placitaver. quod ipsi non fuer. inde culpabiles, &amp; de eo posuer. se su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Patriam, ac postea, (scilicet) eo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:95896:9"/>Termino Sanct. <hi>Hillarii</hi> in ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem Cur. apud <hi>Westm.</hi> predict. praedict. Felonia &amp; Murdro per Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram. praedict. ill. debita juris forma triati suerunt, &amp; inde legitimè con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victi &amp; attincti prout per Record. inde in eadem Curiam Dom. Regis coram ipso Rege apud <hi>Westminst.</hi> praedict. residend. plenius apparet. Quodque pro altis proditionibus &amp; proditoriis, conspirationibus &amp; conju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rationibus praedict. quidam <hi>Edvardus Coleman</hi> &amp; <hi>Willielmus Ireland, Thomas Pickering,</hi> &amp; <hi>Johannes Grove,</hi> ac <hi>Thomas White</hi> alias <hi>Whitebread, Willielmus Harcourt</hi> alias <hi>Harrison, Johannes Fenwick, Johannes Gavan,</hi> &amp; <hi>Antonius Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,</hi> ac <hi>Richardus Langhorne</hi> Arm. existen. Papistae &amp; Superstition. Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manam prositentes ante predict. deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum tertium diem <hi>Januarii,</hi> Anno tricesimo secundo supradicto debito modo &amp; secundum Legis hujus reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni <hi>Angliae</hi> formam, triat. convict. &amp; attinct. fuer. (scil.) praedict. <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vardus Coleman</hi> Termino Sanct. <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaelis</hi> Anno regni Dom. Regis nunc Tricesimo, in Cur. Dom. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis coram ipso Rege (eadem Cur. apud <hi>Westm.</hi> in Com. <hi>Middl.</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunc &amp; adhuc existen.) prout per Recordum &amp; processum inde in ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem Cur. residen. plenius apparet: ac praedict. <hi>Willielmus Ireland; Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Pickering</hi> &amp; <hi>Johannes Grove,</hi> ad deliberation. Gaole Dom. Regis de <hi>Newgate,</hi> tenend. pro dicto Com. <hi>Midd.</hi> apud <hi>Justice-Hall</hi> in le <hi>Old Bailey</hi> in Suburbiis dictae Civitatis <hi>London.</hi> in mense <hi>Decembris,</hi> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no tricesimo supradicto, prout per Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordum &amp; processum inde in custod. <hi>Custodis Rotulorum</hi> dict. Com. <hi>Midd.</hi> reman. plenius apparet: ac predict. <hi>Thomas White</hi> alias <hi>Whitebread, Johannes Fenwick, Willielmus
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:95896:9"/>Harcourt</hi> alias <hi>Harrison, Johannes Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>avn,</hi> &amp; <hi>Antonius Turner</hi> ad delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rationem Goale Dom. Regis de <hi>Newgate</hi> tent. per adjornament pro Cont. <hi>Midd.</hi> praed apud praed. Justicchal in le <hi>Old Bai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley</hi> in Suburbiis Civitatis <hi>London,</hi> die <hi>Veneris</hi> decimo tertio die <hi>Junii,</hi> Anno regni dic. Dom. Regis nunc tricessimo primo pro ut per Recordum &amp; proces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sum inde in custodia dic. Custodis rottol. ejusdem Com. <hi>Midd.</hi> remanend. plenius apparet &amp; praed. <hi>Rich. Lang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horne</hi> ad deliberationem Gaole dic. Regis de <hi>Newgate</hi> tent. per adjorna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment pro dic. Civit. <hi>London</hi> apud Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sticehall in le <hi>Old Bailey</hi> in Parochia St. <hi>Sepulchri</hi> in Warda de <hi>Farring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> extra <hi>London</hi> die Sabbaii decimo quarto die <hi>Junii,</hi> Anno Tricessinto pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo super dic. pro ut per Record. &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cess. inde in custod. Custodis rottol. dic. Civitat. <hi>London</hi> remanend. plenius ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paret) Quodque <hi>Willielmus</hi> Comes <hi>Powis, Willielmus</hi> Vicecomes <hi>Stafford, Henricus</hi> Dom. <hi>Arundel</hi> de <hi>Wardor, Willielmus</hi> Dom. <hi>Petre,</hi> &amp; <hi>Johannes</hi> Dom. <hi>Bellasis,</hi> Trecessimo die <hi>Novem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bris</hi> Anno regni dic. Dom. Regis nunc Tricessimo super dic. apud. <hi>Westmin.</hi> praed. in praed. Com. <hi>Midd.</hi> de altis proditionibus &amp; proditoriis conspirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onib. &amp; conjurationibus praed. legitime accusati &amp; super inde Prisone Dom. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis, scil. <hi>Turri London</hi> Comiss. fuer ibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem salvo custodiend. ac in custodia sic existend. iidem <hi>Williel.</hi> Comes <hi>Powis, Williel.</hi> Vicecomes <hi>Stafford, Henricus</hi> Dom. <hi>Arundel</hi> de <hi>Wardor, Williel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus</hi> Dom. <hi>Petre,</hi> &amp; <hi>Johannes</hi> Dom. <hi>Bellasis</hi> ad <hi>Parliamen' dic. Dom.
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:95896:10"/>Regis nunc apud <hi>Westm.</hi> praed sexto die <hi>Martij</hi> Anno regni sui tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesimo primo teut. per Communes hujus regni <hi>Anglie</hi> in codem Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mento assemblat coram Magnatib. &amp; procerib. ejusdem regni in Parliamento illo convocat &amp; convent. de eo quod per multos Annos tunc ult preterit' pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditoria &amp; execrabilis conspiratio &amp; comiuratio infra hoc regnum <hi>Anglie</hi> &amp; alibi machinat. &amp; prosecut' fuit per Papistas ad alterand. nutand &amp; subuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend. antiquas gubernation. &amp; Leges hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jus regni &amp; nationis &amp; ad suppri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend, veram Religionem in eisdem sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilit' &amp; ad extirpand. &amp; distruend. Professores inde que quidem conspira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio &amp; comiuratio. machinat. &amp; prose<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cut' suisset in diversis Locis &amp; per se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peral, vias &amp; media &amp; per magnum numerdum personar. seperal. qualitatum &amp; gradium que agebant in eisdem &amp; intendebant per inde ad exequend. &amp; consummand. praed. scelerat' &amp; prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torias machinationes &amp; proposita. Quodque die. <hi>Willielmus</hi> Comes <hi>Powis, Willielmus</hi> Vicecomes <hi>Stafford, Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricus</hi> Dom. <hi>Arundel</hi> de <hi>Wardor, Willielmus</hi> Dom. <hi>Petre,</hi> &amp; <hi>Johan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes</hi> Dom. <hi>Bellasis,</hi> simul cum <hi>Phil. Howard</hi> com voc. Cardinal de <hi>Norff. Thoma White alias White<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bread,</hi> com' voc. Provincial. Jesui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, in <hi>Anglia, Rich. Strange</hi> nuper voc. Provincial. Jesuitar. in <hi>Anglia, Vincent.</hi> com' voc Provincial. Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minicor. in <hi>Anglia, Jacobo Corker,</hi> com' voc. President Benedictinor. <hi>Johanne Warner</hi> alias <hi>Clare</hi> Baro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netto, <hi>Williel. Harcourt, Johanne Keins, Nicho. Blundel, Pool, Edvar. Mico, Thoma Bedinfield</hi> alias <hi>Benefield, Basil. Langworth, Carolo Peters, Rich. Peters, Joan.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:95896:10"/>Conyers,</hi> dom. <hi>Georgio Wakeman, Anglice,</hi> Sir <hi>George Wakeman, Thoma Fenwick, Dominick Kelly, <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                           <desc> _____ </desc>
                        </gap> Fitz-Gerrald, <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                           <desc> _____ </desc>
                        </gap> Evers,</hi> Dom. <hi>Thoma Preston Anglice</hi> Sir <hi>Thomas Preston, Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lielm' Lovel</hi> Jesuitis, Dom. <hi>Balte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, Johannes Carrel, Johannes Townely, Rich. Langhorne, Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lielm' Fogarty, Thoma Penny, Mattheo Medbourne, Edvard. Cole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, Willielm' Ireland, Johanne Grove, Thoma Pickering, Johanne Smith,</hi> &amp; diversis aliis Jesuitis sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerdotib. sratrib. <hi>Anglice</hi> Fryers &amp; alils personis ut falsi proditores Dom. Regi nunc et huic regno infra Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus ult. praed. proditorie consuluissent machinat. fuissent &amp; egissent ad &amp; pro consummatione. dict. improbar. per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitiosar. &amp; proditoriar. machination. &amp; ea de causa nequissime &amp; proditorie agreassent conspirassent &amp; determinas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent imprisonare deponere &amp; murdrare sacram Majestatem Dom. Regis nuno &amp; ipsum de regali statu corona &amp; dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitate suis de privare &amp; per malicio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sam &amp; advisat. Locutionem Scriptio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem &amp; alit. declarassent tal. sua pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posita &amp; intentiones ac etiam hoo regnum &amp; nationem Pape &amp; tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice sue Gubernacioni subijcere &amp; status &amp; hereditates Protestant. sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit. Dom Regis seizere. &amp; int. sese par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiri ac erige. &amp; restituere Abbatias, Monasteria. &amp; al. Convent. &amp; Societates quo dudum per Leges hujus regni pro superstitione. &amp; Idololatria suis sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>press. fuissent &amp; eis tradere &amp; resti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuere terras &amp; possessiones in Dom. Rege nunc &amp; subditis suis per leges &amp; Statuta hujus regni vestit ac etiam nova Monasteria &amp; Conventus fundare &amp; erige' &amp; omnes Protestant. Episcopos. &amp; al. personas Ecclesiasticas ab officiis bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiis
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:95896:11"/>&amp; promotionib suis amovere et de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>privare et eo modo personam dom. Regis. nunc distruere protestanteni Religionem extirpare jura libertates &amp; proprieta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes omnium probor. subditor. Dom. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis overtere Legalem gubernationem hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jus regni subvertere &amp; idem Tyrannidi sedis <hi>Romane</hi> subjicere. Quodque dic. Conspiratores &amp; eorum participes &amp; Confederatores proditorie habuissent &amp; tenuissent separales conventiones as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>semblationes &amp; consultationes in quibus inter eos machinat. &amp; designat. fuissent que media utentur &amp; que persone &amp; Instrumenta imploi' forent ad Dom. Regem nunc murderand. &amp; ad tunc &amp; ibidem determinassent id efficere per ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefic' displosionem Anglice <hi>Shooting</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forationem Anglice <hi>Stabbing,</hi> vel ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qua tal. vias &amp; media &amp; obtulissent munera &amp; permissiones de advantag. seperalib. personis ad idem exequend. ac conduxissent &amp; impendissent seperales improbas personas ire ad <hi>Windsor</hi> &amp; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia Loca ubi Dom. Rex residebat ad ipsum Dom. Regem murderand, &amp; di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struend. que quidem persone seu earum aliqu' talia munera acceptassent &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petrationem inde suscepissent &amp; actualit. ad dic. Loca intentione &amp; proposito ill' ivissent. Quodque dic. Conspiratores ad melius per implend. proditorias suas machinationes consuluissent ad Levand. ac procurassent &amp; Levassent homines monetam equos arma &amp; ammunitionem ac etiam applicationem fecissent ad &amp; tractassent &amp; correspendissent cum Papa, ejus Cardinalib. Nunciis, &amp; Agentib. &amp; aliis forinsecis Ministris &amp; personis ad Levand. &amp; obtinend. supplementa, Anglice <hi>supplies</hi> homin. monet. armor. &amp; ammunitionis: cum eisdem facere levare &amp; excitare guerram rebellionem &amp; tumultus infra hoc regn. &amp; idem invadere cum virib. forinsecis &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehendere Anglice <hi>to supprise</hi> sesire &amp; distruere regie Majestatis classem Ang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:95896:11"/>
                     <hi>Navy</hi> fortalitia Angl' <hi>Forts</hi> armamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taria Anglice <hi>Magazines</hi> et Loca fortia, Angl' <hi>places of strength</hi> infra hoc regn. super quo calamitates guerre murdra in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocenc' subditor' viror' mulier' et Liberor' conflagrationes rapine devastationes et al' tremend' miserie et exitia inevitabil. insequerentur in ruinam et destructio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem hujus nationis et quod dic. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spiratores procurassent et acceptassent ac deliberassent seperat' instrumenia Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missiones et protestates per et subt' Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pam vel al' illicitam et usurpat autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritatem ad levand' et disponend' homines monetam, armd et al' necessaria pro eor' sceleratis et proditoriis machina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionib. ac nominatim Commissionem pro dic. <hi>Henrico</hi> Dom. <hi>Arundel</hi> de <hi>Wardor</hi> fore Dom. Cancellar. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glie, aliam Commission' dic. <hi>Williel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m'</hi> Comit. <hi>Powis</hi> fore Dom. The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saurarium Anglie, aliam Commission' dic. <hi>Johanne</hi> Dom <hi>Bellasis</hi> fore du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem General. Anglice, General Exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus levand' al' Commissionem dic' <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lielmus</hi> Dom. <hi>Petre</hi> fore locum tenen' ducis <hi>General</hi> Anglice <hi>Lievtenant General</hi> dic' exercitus et potestatem Anglice, <hi>a power,</hi> pro dic. <hi>Willelmus</hi> Vicecomite <hi>Stafford</hi> fore Expendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torem Anglice <hi>Paymaster</hi> exercitus illius. Quodque in ordine ad animand. seipsos in prosecutione dictar' sceler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atar' conjurationum conspiration' et pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition' et ad celand' et impediend' detectionem earundem et seipsos a Justicia et punitione securand' Conspiratores praed' participes et Confederatores sui usi suissent multis impiis et diabolicis praxib. videlt. causassent sacerdotes suos administrare dic' Conspirato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rib. juramentum taciturnitatis Anglice <hi>of secrecy,</hi> vna cum ecr' sacramento ac etiam causassent dic' Sacerdotes suos super Confessionib. dare absolutiones suas
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:95896:12"/>sub conditione quod ipsi concelarent dic' Conspirationem ac cum circae mensem. <hi>Septembris</hi> tunc ult' pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terit' Dom. <hi>Edmund burry Godfrey</hi> miles Justic. pacis secundum' jura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menti &amp; Officii sui debit' cepisset se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peral. examinationes &amp; informationes concern' prefat' conspirationem &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurationem dic' conspiratores seu eor' aliqui per advisamentum assensum con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sil' &amp; instigationem resid' eor' incitas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent &amp; procurassent diversas personas in insidiis jacere &amp; insequer. prefat' <hi>Edmundbury Godfrey</hi> diversis Dieb. ea intentione ad ipsum murdrand' quod postea per eos perpetrat' &amp; effectum fuit, (pro quib. praed' horridis criminib' &amp; offensis <hi>Robertus Green, Henricus Berry,</hi> &amp; <hi>Laurentius Hill,</hi> pastea at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tincti fuissent, ac <hi>Dominick Kelly,</hi> &amp; <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                        <desc> _____ </desc>
                     </gap>
                     <hi>Girald,</hi> &amp; alii fugam fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cissent per eisdem) post quod quidem murdrum &amp; antequam cadaver invent' fuit vel murdrum cognitum aliquibus, nisi Participibus in eodem dic. person' false. retuler' quod vivus fuit &amp; privatim maritat' &amp; postquam cadaver invent' fuit disperser' falsam' &amp; malitiosam re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lationem quod ipse seipsum murdrasset. Quod quidem murdrum commissum fuit ea intentione ad celand' &amp; suppri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend' evidentiam quam ipse cepisset ac de qua notitiam habuit &amp; ad intimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dand' &amp; deterrend' Magistrat. &amp; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lios ab agendo in ulteriori detectione conspirationis &amp; conjurationis praed'ea enim intentione dic. <hi>Edmundbury Godfrey</hi> dum vivus fuit per eos ac participes &amp; fautores suos minatus &amp; deterritus fuit in ejus prosecutione inde quodque de eor' ulteriori malicia scele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate machinati fuissent per quam plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimas suggestiones impon' imputationem &amp; culpam praed' horridor' &amp; detestabil' criminum super protestantes ita quod
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:95896:12"/>perinde ipsimet evitarent punitiones quas juste meruissent. &amp; exponerent protestantes scandalo magno &amp; eos sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jicerent prosecutioni &amp; oppressio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni in omnib, regnis &amp; patriis ubi Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mena Religio recepta &amp; professa suit quodque omnia ill proditiones crimina &amp; offense prementionat' fuer' machinat. commiss perpetrat' act a &amp; facta per praed. <hi>Willielm'</hi> Comitens <hi>Powis, Willielm</hi> Vicecomitem <hi>Stafford, Willielmus</hi> Dom. <hi>Petre. Henricum</hi> Dom <hi>Arun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>del</hi> de <hi>Wardor,</hi> &amp; <hi>Johannem</hi> Dom. <hi>Bellasis</hi> ac alios conspiratores praed contr. Dom. Regemnunc coronatis &amp; dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitat' suas ac contr. Leges &amp; Statuta hujus regni) secund' Legem &amp; consuetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinem Parliament' impetit? fuer' acinde debite onerak' &amp; in Prisona praed. ea oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casione dent' pro ut per Record &amp; process. inde int. recorda Parliament' remanend plonius apparet. Et iidem Maior &amp; Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monal' ac Cives Civitat. <hi>London</hi> ulterius dicunt quod in. Session. praed. Parliamenti dic. Dom. Regis nunc apud <hi>Westmin.</hi> praed. per proragation. tenet. super praed. vicessimum print. diem. <hi>Octobris,</hi> Anno regni dic. Dom, Regis nunc Tricessimose<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundo super dic' in replicatione praed. men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionat'. ad inchoation' ejusdem Sessionis. Dom. Rex. nunc ex maxima regali cura &amp; sedulitate sua pro preservatione reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gionis protesta<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>' &amp; subditor' suor' a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riculis per papisticas conspirationes eis im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minen' per ejus graciosam oration' ambab'
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:95896:13"/>domibus euisdom Parliamenti ad tunc &amp; ibidem fact &amp; allocut' inter alias recommendavit Dom. et Comman' in Parliamento illo assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blat' ad prosequend' ultiorent exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nationem Conspiration' praed' cum strict a &amp; impartiali inquisitone, et eis tune dixit quod ipse non puta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit seipsunt neque ipsos secur' quous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que materia illa plenarie perageretur. Ac ideo quod necessar' foret quod praed' Dom. in praed' prisona Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris <hi>London</hi> ad celeremtriation' suant adducentur quod justicia fieret. Et idem <hi>Major</hi> et Commonal' ac Cives Civitat: <hi>London'</hi> ulterius dicunt quod postea in eadem Session' Parliamenti utraque domus Parliamenti illius in proscution' dic' direction' Dom. Regis strictam et impartialem inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition' de praed. conspiratione fecer' et super inquisition' ill' declaraver' quod suisset horribilis Conspiratio et conjuratio per papistas contra person<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>av<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> dic. Dom. Regis et Gubernation' suam que tunc continuabant; ac Common' in eodem Parliamento assemblat' ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terius declaraverunt quod Conspiratio et Conjuratio. ill' supportat' et prosecut' fuissent per poten' et irrequiet' moli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mina et machinationes presertim du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ran' tunc nuperis recessib. Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menti et postea in eadem Sessione Parliamenti Dom. Sprituales et Temporales ac Communes in co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem Parliamento assemblat' eorum
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:95896:13"/>humilem Supplicationem Anglice <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dress</hi> eidem Domino Regi apud <hi>Westm'</hi> praed' fecer' &amp; exhibuer in forma sequen' videl' Quod ipst Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diti Regie sue Majestatis obsequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tissimi &amp; fidelissimi Dom' Spirituales &amp; Temporales ac Communes in tunc praesenti Parliamento illo assemblat' profunde sensibiles existen' de tristi &amp; calamitosa conditione hujus Regni pracipue per impias &amp; horrendas Conspirationes Papalis Factionis cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sat' que non solum destructionem Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>galis Persone Regie sue Majestatis verumetiam totalem subversionem Gu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernat' &amp; vere Religion' in hoc Regno <hi>Anglie</hi> stabilit' conspiravisset &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendasset ac invenien' easdem detesta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biles machinationes adtunc obstinate per eandem Factionem prosecut' tam fovendo divisiones int' Majestatis sue fideles Subdit' Protestan' quam per omnes al' nequissimas machinationes non obstan' quamplurimis detectioni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus inde (magna Dei misericordia &amp; mirabili providentia) tunc nuper in lucem prolat' que omnia tremenda judicia tunc fuer' super hoc Regnum impenden' pro pluribus &amp; gravibus suis peccatis quam meritissime ac alit' humana ratione evitari nequibant quam per benediction' Dei particula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem super consultationes &amp; conamina magni concilii ipsius Dom' Regis tunc in Parliamento assemblat' in omni humilitate Regie sue Majestati sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicaver' quod per Proclamation' su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am Regalem dies solempnit' foret de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicat' in quo tam ipsi quam omnes ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sius Dom' Regis Subdit' per jejun' &amp; preces Deo omnipotenti reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem conarentur Ac cum cordibus humilibus &amp; penitentibus eum implo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarent per ejus potentiam &amp; bonita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem ad judicia ill' divertend' &amp; ad impia consdia &amp; machinationes ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micorum suorum frustrand' ad corda
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:95896:14"/>sidelium Protestan' Subdit' dict' Dom' Regis uniend' &amp; ad misericordiam suam &amp; Evangelii set lumen eidem Domino Regi &amp; dictis Subdit' suis &amp; eor' Posteritat' continuand' ac pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipue ad abundantes benedictiones suas super sacram Majestatem ipsius Dom' Regis &amp; tunc presen' Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment' impendend' quod consultationes &amp; conamina eor' honorem incolumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem &amp; prosperitatem Regie sue Majestati ac Populo suo producerent &amp; superinde dictus Dominus Rex nunc duran' dicta Sessione Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menti scilicet secundo die <hi>Decem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bris</hi> Ano Regni sui tricesimo secundo supradicto per Proclamationem suam regalem sub Magno Sigillo suo <hi>Ang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie</hi> Sigillat' geren' Dat' apud <hi>Westm'</hi> eisdem die &amp; anno recitando quod cum Dom' Spirituales &amp; Temporales ac Communes in Parliamento illo as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>semblat' per eor' Supplication' An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glice <hi>Address</hi> eidem Domino Regi ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibit' notum ei fecissent quod ipsi profunde sensibiles fuer' de tristi &amp; calamitosa conditione hujus Regni per impias &amp; horrendas Conspirationes Papalis Factionis causat' que non solum destructionem Regalis Persone Regie sue Majestatis verumetiam to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal' subversionem Gubernat' &amp; vere Religionis apud ipsum Regem &amp; Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditos suos stabilit' conspiravisset &amp; intendisset quodque eedem detestabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les machinationes adtunc obstinate per eandem Factionem prosecut' fuer, tam fovendo divisiones int' ejus fideles Subdit' Protestan' quam per omnes al' nequissimas machinationes non ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stan' quamplurimis detectionibus inde (magna Dei misericordia &amp; mirabili providentia) tunc nuper in lucem pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lat' que omnia tremenda judicia tunc fuer' super eundem Dominum Regem &amp;
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:95896:14"/>dictos Subdit' suos impenden' pro plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus &amp; gravibus suis peccatis quam meritissime ac alit' humana ratione preveniri nequibant quam per bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictionem Dei particularem super consultationes &amp; conamina Magni Concilii ipsius Dom' Regis tunc in Parliamento assemblat' eidem Domino Regi humillime supplicassent quod dies maxime solempnit' foret dedicat' in quo Rex ipsemet &amp; omnes Subditi sui fideles per jejunium &amp; preces Deo omnipotenti reconciliationem conaren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur ac cum cordibus humilibus &amp; pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitentibus eum implorarent per ejus potentiam &amp; bonitatem ad judicia illa divertend' &amp; ad impia consilia &amp; machinationes inimicorum ipsius Dom' Regis &amp; dict' Subdit' suor' fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strand' ac corda fidelium Protestan' Subdit' dict' Dom' Regis uniend' &amp; misericordiam suam &amp; Evangelii sui lumen eidem Domino Regi &amp; dictis Subdit' suis &amp; eor' Posteritat' conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuand' ac precipue ad abundantes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedictiones suas super ipsum Dom' Regem &amp; tunc presen' Parliament' impendend' quod consultationes &amp; co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namina eor' honorem incolumitatem &amp; prosperitatem dicto Domino Regi ac Populo suo producerent idem Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minus Rex ad illam eor' humilem re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quisitionem pnomptissime inclinavit ac per illam ejus Regalem Proclamation' mandavit generale &amp; publicum Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junium per totum hoc Regnum obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vari. in tali modo qualis postea per eandem Proclamationem fuit direct' &amp; prescript' ita quod tam idem Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minus Rex quam Populus suus preces &amp; supplicationes suas Deo omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenti emitterent ad &amp; pro proposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis predict' ac ea intentione quod tam Religiosum Exercitium ad unum
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:95896:15"/>&amp; idem tempus performaretur dictus Dominus Rex per Proclamation' ill' publicavit &amp; declaravit omnibus Subditis suis amantibus ac stricte precepit &amp; mandavit quod die <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curii</hi> existen' vicesimo secundo die <hi>Decembris</hi> tunc instan' jejunium ill' religiose observat' &amp; celebrat' foret per Regnum suum <hi>Anglie</hi> Dominium <hi>Wallie</hi> &amp; Villam <hi>Berwici super Twedam</hi> &amp; ut idem cum omni de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centia &amp; uniformitate performaretur idem Dominus Rex per advisamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum reverend' Episcopor' suor' com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poni imprimi &amp; publicari direxerat talem formam Divini Servicii qual' ipse apt' uti censuerat in omnibus Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesiis &amp; Locis ad tempus pred' &amp; Episcopis suis dederat in mandatis ad ill' congruent' dispergend' Que omnia idem Dominus Rex per Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamationem suam pred' reverent' &amp; decent' observari expresse precepit &amp; mandavit per omnes Subdit' suos amantes sicut favorem Dei omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentis respexer' ac iram &amp; indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion' ejus contra hanc terram evita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent &amp; sub pena subeundi tales pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitiones qual' dictus Dominus Rex juste infligere posset super omnes què tam religiosum Officium contemnerent seu negligerent prout per irrotula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment' ejusdem Proclamationis in Cur' <hi>Cancellar'</hi> ipsius Dom' Regis de Ré<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordo remanen' plenius apparet Qui quidem dies Jejunii secundum formam &amp; effect' Proclamat' pred' debite &amp; solempnit' observat' &amp; celebrat' fuit in &amp; per totum hoc Regnum <hi>Anglie</hi> ac precipue apud <hi>London'</hi> predict' in Parochia &amp; Warda predict' Quodque in eadem Sessione Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menti ult' mentionat' Communes hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jus Regni in eodem Parliamento
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:95896:15"/>assemblat. resolution. pro cedere ad tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ationem predict. Dominor. in Prisona <hi>Turris London.</hi> tunc existen. sic ut prefertur impetit. &amp; Statim incipere cum prefat. Vicecomite <hi>Stafford</hi> ac no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticiam inde Dominis Parliamenti illi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us tunc deder. &amp; eos requisiver. ad con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venien. diem pro triatione ejusdem Vicecomitis <hi>Stafford</hi> appunctuand. &amp; superinde predist. Vicecomes <hi>Stafford</hi> de altis proditionibus &amp; proditoriis conspirationibus &amp; conjurationibus predict unde ipse ut prefertur impetit. fuit per Dominos temporales in eodem Parliamento convent. ad prosecution. Commun. hujus Regni in Parliamento illo assemblat. in eadem Sessione Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menti triat. convict. &amp; debita juris forma attinct. fuit pro ut per Record &amp; process inde inter Recorda Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. remanen. plentus apparet post<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ea<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>; in eadem Sessione Parliamenti <hi>Willielmus Scrogs</hi> Miles tunc Capital Justic. Dicti Domini Regis ad placita coram ipso Rege tenend assign. per Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munes hujus Regni Anglie in eodem Parliamento assemblat. coram Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natibus &amp; proceribus ejusdem Regni in Parliamento illo convocat. &amp; convent. secundum Legem &amp; consuetudinem Parliamenti accusat. &amp; impetit. fuit. de alta proditione &amp; aliis magnis crim<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nibus &amp; malegest ris inter alia quod ipse dictus <hi>Willielmus Scrogs</hi> tunc existen. Capital Justic. Cur. Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mint Regis coram ipso Rege prodito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie &amp; nequit. conat. fuisset subvert. Leges fundamental. &amp; stabilit. Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. &amp; gubernation. hujus Regni Anglie ac loco inde introducere Papi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stum Anglice <hi>Popery</hi> &amp; Arbitrariam &amp; Tyrannicam gubernationem contrà Legem quod ipse declarasset per diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sa proditoria &amp; improba verba opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niones judicia praxes &amp; facta: Ac
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:95896:16"/>Ac etiam quod cum fuisset horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilis &amp; diabolica conspiratio machi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat. &amp; prosecut. per Papistas pro murdrando Domin. Regem nunc sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertendo Leges &amp; gubernation. hujus Regni &amp; pro distruendo Religionem Protestan. in eodem Regno, que omnia divers. <hi>Willielmus Scrogs</hi> bene sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>visset in quantum ipsemet non solum triasset verum etiam sudicium reddi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>disset contra seperal. hujusmodi delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quentium, nihilominus dictus <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lielmus Scrogs</hi> ad diversa tempora &amp; loca tam in Cur. seden. quam alit, palam defamasset &amp; scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalizasset sepiral. de testibus qui probas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent dictos proditiones contra diversos conspiratoribus &amp; dedissent evidenci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am contra diversas altas personas que tunc fuer. nomine triat. ac conatus fuisset defamare Anglice <hi>to disparage</hi> eor. evidenciam &amp; adimere creden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciam eorum per quod quantum in se fuit proditorie &amp; nequit. suppressisset &amp; suffocasset detectionem dicte papalis conspirationis ac animasset conspirator<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es (ad procedend. in eadem) in magnum &amp; manifestum periculum sacrae vitae dicti Domini Regis nunc &amp; bene Stabilit. gubernation. &amp; Religionis hujus Regni Anglie pro ut per Record. inde inter Record Parliament. remanen. plentus apparet. Ac etiam in eadem Sessione Parliamenti Domini Spirituales &amp; Temporales ac Communes in eodem Parliamento assemblat. se de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claraver. eis manifest. esse quod ad tunc fuit &amp; per diversos Annos tunc ult. elaps. fuisset horrenda &amp; prodito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria conspiratio &amp; conjuratio machi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat. &amp; prosecut. per ill de papali Religione in Regno Hibernie pro trucidatione Anglice <hi>Massacreing,</hi> Anglor. &amp; subvertion. Religionis protestan. &amp; antique stabilit guber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nationis Regni illius de qua quidem horrenda &amp; proditoria conspiratione &amp; conjuratione Ricardus Power Comes Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rone
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:95896:16"/>in Regno Hibernie ad eandem Session Parliamenti per Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes hujus Regni Anglie in eodem Parliamento assemblat. coram Magnatibus &amp; proceribus ejusdem Regni Anglie in Parliamento illo convocat. &amp; convent. secundum Legem &amp; consuetudinem Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menti impetit. fuit. ac inde de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bite onerat. &amp; Prisone Domin. Regis de le <hi>Gatehouse Westm.</hi> ea Occasione Commissus fuit pro ut per Record inde inter Recorda Parliament. remanen' plenius ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paret quodque tam Domin. quam Communes in dicto Parliamento assemblat. in eadem Sessione Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liamenti fuer. preparantes billas secundum cursum Parliament. in Leges inactitand' pro preservatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne Domini Regis nunc &amp; subdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torum suorum protestan. contra proditorias conspirationes &amp; conju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rationes predicta penden. quibus qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem Seperalis impeticionibus versus eundem Ricardum <hi>Power</hi> &amp; dictum <hi>Willielm. Scrogs</hi> ac predict. <hi>Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elm.</hi> Comitem <hi>Powis Henricum</hi> Dominum <hi>Arundel</hi> de <hi>Wardour Willielm.</hi> Domin. <hi>Petre</hi> &amp; <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hannem</hi> Domin. <hi>Bellasis</hi> minime determinat. ac eisd<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m <hi>Willielm.</hi> Comite <hi>Powis Henrico</hi> Domino <hi>Arundel</hi> de <hi>Wardour Willielm.</hi> Domin. <hi>Petre<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Johanne</hi> Domin. <hi>Bellasis</hi> &amp; <hi>Ricardo Power</hi> in Prison. Domini Regis ex causis predict. ut prefertur existen. idem Parliament. super predict. deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum diem <hi>Januarii</hi> Anno Regni dicti Domin. Regis nunc tricessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo secundo superdicto prorogat. suit pro ut predict. Attorn. dict. Domin. Regis nunc Generalis superius inde allegavit absque aliqua tria<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tione dictor. <hi>Willi.</hi> Co-Comit.</hi>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:95896:17"/>
                  <hi>Powis Henric.</hi> Domin. Arun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>del de <hi>Wardour Willielm.</hi> Domin. <hi>Petre Johan.</hi> Domin. <hi>Bellasis Willielm. Scrogs</hi> &amp; <hi>Ricard. Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi> seu eorum alicujus de altis pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction. &amp; al. premissis unde ipsi respective ut prefertur impetit. fuer. (ac qui aliter quam in Parliament ind. triari non po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuer.) fact. sive habetur ac ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam hujusmodi bille in Leges in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actitat. fuer. Que quidem Oratio dicti Domin. Regis ac Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ones &amp; processus Domin. &amp; Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mun. Parliamenti illtus duran. dicta Sessione ejusdem Parliamenti ut prefertur fact. ante eandem Prorogationem Parllamenti illius publicat. fuer. videlt. apud <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> predict in predicta Parochia Sancti <hi>Michaelis Bassishaw</hi> in Warda predicta ratione quorum quidem premissor. Cives &amp; Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitan. predict. Civitatis <hi>London</hi> fideles subditer dicti Domin. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis nunc existen. maxime perte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riti. &amp; in animis affecti ac quam plur mum inquietat, fuer. pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fundo sensu &amp; apprehentione mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor. periculor. persone Domin. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis nunc &amp; gubernationi sue hujus Regni ac Religioni Protestan. &amp; professoribus ejusdem occasione con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spiration. predict. impenden. &amp; munen non aliter. (pro ut per Domin. Spirituales &amp; Temporales ac Communes in dicto Parliamento assemblat. in supplicatione sua predict. per Domin. Regem in Proclamat. predict. ut prefert. publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat. affirmat. humana ration. evitand.
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:95896:17"/>qu' per Benidictionem Dei perticu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larem super consultationes &amp; cona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mina ejusdem Parliamenti, Quidam cives &amp; inhabitantes ejusdem. civi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis, nomine civum &amp; inhabitanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um dict' civitatis ante Petitionem in praedicto placito praed' Attorn' General' surcius replicando placitat' spec' fact' seu fieri ordinat' scil. Praed' tertio Decimo Die Januarii Anno Regni dict' Dom' Regis nunc tricesimo secund' super dict' <hi>Patient' Ward</hi> Miles, tunc, Maiori Civitatis London &amp; Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derm' dict' Civitatis ac Communia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riis sive Civib' de Com' concilio e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jusdem Civitatis in Communi Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilio adtunc predicta Camera Guild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hal' ejusdem Civitatis in parochia Sti' <hi>Michaelis'</hi> Bassieshaw predict' se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cun' consuetudinem dicte Civitatis as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>semblat' exhibuer' quandam Petitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem continend' quod ipsi Cives &amp; inhabitan' civitat' London profunde sensibiles existen' de malis &amp; exitiis super hanc nationem in generali ac ill' civitatem Lond' in particulari penden' in respect' periculi persone Dom' Regis nunc Religion' Protestand' &amp; bene Stabilit' guberacion' sue per continuat' infernales &amp; diabolicas ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chinaciones Papistar' &amp; alior' ad heren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium suor' ac scientes nullam viam (sub Deo) tam effectual' preservand' Dom. Regem ac cives &amp; inhabitand' ill' ab extrem' ruina &amp; destructione minat' quam per celerem Sessionem tunc pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sentis Parliamen' (cujus inopinata Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatio magnopere addidit et augebat justos timores &amp; suspiciones Animor'
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:95896:18"/>dictor' Petitionarior' ipsi iidem Petito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res obsecra ver? eidem Com. Concilio ut prefertur assemblat' ad informand' regiam Majestatem de ill' eor' timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus &amp; apprehensionibus ac quod fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it, humile &amp; fervens desideriam tam eor' Petitor' quam ipsor' Maioris &amp; Aldermanor' ac Commaneor' de Com. Concilio illo quod Regiae sue Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jestati placeret pro totali frustratione impior' &amp; sang uiolentor' propositor' Inimicor' sucr' ad permittend' ill' tunc present' Parliamentum quod extitit prorogat' usque vicesimum diem tunc instand' Januarii adtunc assemblare &amp; sedend' continuare quousque effectualit' securaret hoc Regnum contra Papism' ac reformaret Anglice redressed mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplicia gravamina sub quibus tunc gemuit &amp; pro immediate securitate sud quod iidem Maior &amp; Alderm' ac Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muniarii de Com. concilio ill' ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent quod cunque aliud quod necessar' &amp; expedien' eis videretur in illo Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore periculi imminen' per incolumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate magne Civitatis illius Et quia per legem terre hujus Regni Angliae Licitum est subdit' Dom' Regis in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustiis &amp; difficultalib' suis ad humilli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me supplicand' Dom. Regi pro reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dio congruo in ea parte habend' praed' die Jovis decimo tertio die Januarii Anno Regni dict' Dom' Regis nunc tricesimo secund' supradict' praedict' Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciens <hi>VVard</hi> Miles, tunc Maior pred' Civitatis <hi>London</hi> &amp; Alderm' ejusdem Civitat' (scil' <hi>Thomas Aleyn</hi> Miles, &amp; Bar' <hi>Johannes Fredericke</hi> Miles,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:95896:18"/>
                  <hi>Johannes Lawrence</hi> Miles, <hi>Georgius Waterman</hi> Miles, <hi>Jose<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phus Sheldon</hi> Miles, <hi>Jacobus Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards</hi> Miles, <hi>Robertus Clayton</hi> Miles, <hi>Johannes Moore</hi> Miles, <hi>Gu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lielmus Pritchard</hi> Miles, <hi>Henricus Tulse</hi> Miles, <hi>Jacobus Smith</hi> Miles, <hi>Robertus Jeffrey</hi> Miles, <hi>Johannes Shorter</hi> Miles, <hi>Thomas Gould</hi> Miles, <hi>Gulielmus Rawsterne</hi> Miles, <hi>Thomas Beckford</hi> Miles, <hi>Johannes Chapman</hi> Miles, <hi>Simon Lewis</hi> Meles, <hi>Thomas Pilkinton</hi> Arm' &amp; <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricus Cornish</hi> Arm' ac Communiarti seu Cives de com' Concilio dict' Civi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis in com' concilio suo infra cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem Civitatem (scil' in praed' Camera <hi>Guild-hall</hi> Civitatis illius ad tunc se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond' consue tudinem dict'Civitatis As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>semblat' vota &amp; Suffragia sua ex ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis Dom' Regi per fidelib' &amp; pro sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction' civum &amp; inhabitan' ejus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem Civitat' qui petitionem eis in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma praed' exhibuissent pro allevatione timoris &amp; apprehensionis &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quietudinis illor' ac ea intentione quantum in se fuit pro preservatione persone Dom' Regis nunc &amp; gubernati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion' sue hujus regni Anglie &amp; reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gionis Protestan' deder' ac nemine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicente agreaver' &amp; ordinaver' quod quedam petitio' sub nomine ipsor' Maioris Alderm' et Commun' Civit' <hi>London'</hi> in com' Concilio assemblat' dict' Dom' Regi nunc exhibit foret cujus quidem petitionis tenor' sequitur in his Anglicanis verbis, <hi>viz. To the Kings most Excellent MAJE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STY, The humble Petition of the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:95896:19"/>Lord Mayor, Aldermen &amp; Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of the City of</hi> London <hi>in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Council Assembled, most humbly sheweth, That Your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jestyes Great Council, in</hi> Parliament, <hi>having in their late Session, in pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suance of Your Majestyes direction, entred upon a strict and impartial inquiry into the Horrid and Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crable Popish Plot which hath been for several Years last past, and still is carried on, for Destruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Your Majesties Sacred Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son and Governement, and extirpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Protestant Religion, and the utter Ruine of Your Majesties Protestant Subjects: And having so far proceeded therein, as justly to Attaint, upon full Evidence, one of the Five Lords Impeached for the same, and were in further Prosecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the remaining Four Lords, and other Conspirators there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in: And as well the Lords Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual and Temporal, as the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons in Your said Parliament As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembled, having declared, That they are fully satisfied that there now is, and for divers Years last past, hath been a Horrid and Treasonable Plot, and Conspiracy contrived and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried on by those of the Popish Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion in</hi> Ireland, <hi>for Massacring the</hi> English, <hi>and Subverting the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant Religion, and the Ancient Established Government of that Kingdom: And Your said Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons having Impeached the Earl of</hi> Tyrone, <hi>in order to the bringing him to Justice for the same; and having under Examination, other Conspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rators in the said</hi> Irish <hi>Plot: And Your said Commons having like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise Impeached Sir</hi> William Scroggs, <hi>Chief Justice of Your Majesties Court of</hi> Kings-Bench <hi>for Treason,</hi>
                  <q>
                     <pb n="33" facs="tcp:95896:19"/>
                     <hi>and other great Crimes and Misde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meanors, in endeavouring to subvert the Laws of this Kingdom by his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrary and Illegal Proceedings, and having Voted Impeachments against several other Judges for the like Mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demeanors, your Petitioners consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering the continual hazards to which your sacred Life, and the Protestant Religion, and the Peace of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom are exposed, while the hopes of a Popish Successor gives Countenance and Encouragement to the Conspira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors in their wicked Designs. And considering also the disquiet and dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Apprehensions of your good Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, by reason of the Miseries and Mischiefs which threaten them on all parts, as well from Foreign Powers, as from the Conspiracies within your several Kingdoms, against which no sufficient remedy can be provided but by your Majesty; and your Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment were extreamly surprised at the late Prorogation, whereby the prose<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of the publick Justice of the Kingdom, and the making the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>visions necessary for the Preservation of your Majesty and your Protestant Subjects hath received an interruption. And they are the more affected here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, by reason of the Experience they have had of the great Progress which the emboldned Conspirators have former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly made in their Designs, during the late frequent recesses of Parliament; but that which supports them against Despair, is, the hopes they derive from your Majesties Goodness, that your intention was, and does conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue by this Prorogation, to make way for your better concurrence with the Counsels of your Parliament. And your Petitioners humbly hope that your Majesty will not take offence that your Subjects are thus zealous, and even impatient of the least delay of the long hoped for security, whilst they see your precious Life invaded, the true Religion undermined, their Families and innocent Posterity likely to be subjected to Blood, Confusion and Ruine, and all these dangers encreas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, by reason of the late Endeavours of your Majesty and your Parliament, which have added Provocation to the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:95896:20"/>Conspirators, but have had little or no effect towards securing against them; and they trust your Majesty will gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciously accept of this Discovery, and desire of their Loyal Hearts to preserve your Majesty, and whatever else is dear to them, and to strengthen your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty against all Popish and pernicious Counsels, which any ill affected per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons may presume to offer: They do therefore most humbly pray, that your Majesty will be graciously pleased (as the only means to quiet the minds, and extinguish the fears of your Protestant People, and prevent the eminent dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers which threaten your Majesties Kingdoms, and particularly this your great City, which hath already so deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly suffered for the same) to permit your said Parliament to sit from the day to which they are Prorogued, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til by their Counsels and Endeavours those good remedies shall be provided, and those just ends attained, upon which the safety of your Majesties Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, the preservation of the Protestant Religion, the Peace and Settlement of your Kingdoms, and the welfare of this your ancient City, do so absolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly depend; for the pursuing and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining of which good effects, your Petitioners unanimously do offer their Lives and Estates. And shall ever pray,</hi> &amp;c.</q> Ac adtunc &amp; ibidem ulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius agreaver' &amp; ordinaver' quod Petitio ill' post presentation' inde eidem Dom. Regi im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressa foret per talem personam qual' dictus tunc Major. Civitat' London' praed. appun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuaret Quae quidem Petitio sic fuit im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>primi ordinat. ea intentione quod Publica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio flor. rumor. &amp; relation. de &amp; concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen. Petition. dicto Domino Regi exhibit. evitaretur munici Domini Regis &amp; Conspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratores praed. a procedendo in conspira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione sua praed. deturrerentur perturba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiones quas boni &amp; fideles subditi dicti Domini Regis nunc in animis suis ex causis praedictus concepissent alleviarentur &amp; Cives &amp; Inhabitan. ejusdem Civitat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melius scirent quid factum fuisset in dicto Communi Concilio de materia in Petitione praed. eidem Communi Concilio
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:95896:20"/>ut praefertur exhibit. content. Quod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que praedicta Petitio dicto Dom. Regi sic presentari agreat. postea scilicet praed. decimo tertio die Januarii Anno tricesimo secundo supradicto eidem Dom. Regi humillime praesentat. fuit videlicet apud London praed. in prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicta parochia Sancti Michael. Bassie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shawe in Warda praedict. ac postea scil. decimo quinto die ejusdem mensis Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuarii per Samuelem Roycroft (quem dictus Paciens Ward tunc Major. Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitat. London. ad inde appunctuavit) impressa fuit juxta ordinem praed. in ea parte fact' videlicet apud London. praed. in Parochia &amp; Warda praed. Quae quidem Petitio &amp; impressio inde informa &amp; ex causa praed. fact. sunt eadem Petitio &amp; impressio &amp; publica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio inde in praed. placito praed. At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torn. Generalis superius replicando placitat. spec. Abs{que} hoc quod aliqua Petitio de vel concernen. Prorogation. Parliamenti praed. fact. ordinat. Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licat. seu impress. fuit alit. vel alio modo quam iidem Major. &amp; Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitas ac Cives Civitat. London. supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius allegaver. prout idem Attorn. Generalis pro dicto Domino Rege su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perius suppon. &amp; hoc scilicet Parat. sunt verisicare unde iidem Major. &amp; Communitas ac Cives Civitat. Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don. non intendunt quod ipsi per ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qua praeallegat. praed. Libertat. Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leg. &amp; Franches. fore de seipsis unum Corpus Corporat. &amp; Politicum in re facto &amp; nomine per nomen Majoris &amp; Communitat. ac Civum Civitat. Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don. ac per idem nomen placitare &amp; implacitari respondere ac responderi per ipsos superius ut praefertur cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mat. forisfecer. ac ut Prius Pet. ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicium &amp; quod Libertat. Privileg. &amp; Franches. ill. eis &amp; Successoribus suis imperpetuum deinceps allocentur &amp; adjudicentur ac quod ipsi quoad praemiss. ill. ab hac Cur. dimittantur, &amp;c.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div xml:lang="eng" type="version">
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:95896:2"/>
               <head>The Mayor Commonalty and Citiz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens of <hi>London</hi> at the Suit of our Lord the King.</head>
               <p>ANd the aforesaid Mayor and Commonalty, and Citizens of the City of <hi>London,</hi> as to the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foresaid <hi>Plea</hi> of the aforesaid At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torney General of our said Lord the now King above by replying, plead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in assisting Forfeitures of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, Priviledges and Franchise, following (to Wit) them the Mayor and Commonalty; and Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens of the City of <hi>London</hi> to be of themselves, a Body Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and Politick in deed fact and Name by the Name of the Mayor and Commonalty and Citizens of the City of <hi>London,</hi> and by the same Name to plead, and be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaded, to answer and be answer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto, by them above claimed, protesting that that <hi>Plea,</hi> and the matter in the fame contained are not sufficient in Law, them the Mayor and Commonalty and Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens of the City of <hi>London,</hi> of that Liberty, Priviledge and Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chise, to fore-judge or Exclude Protesting, also that no Act, or Deed nor, any By-Law; made by the Common Council: or by the Mayor, Aldermen and Common Council of the City aforesaid, is the Act, or Deed, of the said Body Corporate and Politick, and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testing also that the said Mayor and Commonalty and Citizens of the City of <hi>London;</hi> contrary to the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:95896:3"/>Trust in them reposed, never assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med upon themselves any unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful or unjust power, to leavy Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney of the Subjects, and Liege peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the King, to the private lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ere and prosit of them, the Mayor and Commonalty, and Citizens of the City of <hi>London,</hi> by Colour of Laws or Ordinances, by them made or ordained as the aforesaid At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torney General of our said Lord the now King, for the same our Lord the King above supposeth, and protesting further that the same Mayor and Commonalty and Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens of <hi>London,</hi> have not lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vied or exacted so great Sums of Money, by the year of persons coming to publick <hi>Markets</hi> held within the said City with Victuals and Provisions, there to be fold as the said Attorney General, for our same Lord the King above hath Alledged. For <hi>Plea</hi> nevertheless, as to the making and publishing the Law for leavying Moneys of persons coming to publick <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets,</hi> held within the City afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said, with Victuals and Provisions there to be sold, and the exacting and leavying of those Moneys a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove supposed to be done. The same Mayor and Commonalty, and Citizens of the City of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> say that the City of <hi>London</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foresaid is, and from the time whereof the memory of man is not to the contrary was the chief and Capital City, and Metropoliss and the Principal Port of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>England,</hi> and in Citizens &amp; Inhabitants most Populous, and in the Concourse of People, as well Liegemen of our Lord the King as Foreigners most abounding and the most renouned Mart-Town of all <hi>Europe,</hi> and that there are now held and kept, and from the time whereof the memory of man is not to the contrary there
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:95896:3"/>were held and kept <hi>publick</hi> Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets within the City aforesaid, for Victuals, Provisions, and other goods and Merchandizes thither brought there to be sold. And that they, the said <hi>Mayor</hi> and <hi>Commonalty,</hi> and <hi>Citizens</hi> of the City of <hi>London</hi> aforesaid on the aforesaid seventeenth day of <hi>Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tember,</hi> in the six and twentleth year aforesaid in the Replication aforesaid mentioned, and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually since, and from the time whereof the <hi>Memory</hi> of <hi>Man</hi> is <hi>nor</hi> to the <hi>contrary</hi> were seized, and yet are <hi>seized</hi> of, and in the <hi>publick</hi> Markets aforesaid in their <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mesne</hi> as of <hi>Fee,</hi> and by that whole time at their own proper Charges have provided and have been accustomed, and ought to provide Market places whore such Markets were held as often as need required, and Stalls, Stand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and other Accommodations for persons coming to the same Markets with Victuals and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>visions there to be sold; or the better and more convenient ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posing the same to Sale: And have provided and appointed O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verseers, and other Officers of those Markets for the preservation of good Order in the same Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets, and for the better regula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the same, and of the great concourse of People thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther resorting; and have cleansed, and have been accustomed, and ought to cleanse the Market pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces aforesaid. And for deliaying their said Charges by the whole time aforesaid, have had and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, and have been accustom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to have and receive divers reasonable Tolls, Rates, or Sums of Money of all persons what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever to the Markets aforesaid so as aforesaid coming for Stalls,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:95896:4"/>Standings, and other Accommoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions by them had for the expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing to Sale such Victuals and Provisions in those Markets. And the same Mayor, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monalty, and Citizens of the City of <hi>London</hi> further say, that the Citizens and Freemen of the City aforesaid, the said seven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth of <hi>September,</hi> in the six and twentieth year abovesaid, alwaies were, and yet are very numerous (to wit) fifty thousand men and more: And that within the said City of <hi>London</hi> (to wit, in the said Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish of St. <hi>Michael Bassieshaw,</hi> in the Ward of <hi>Bassieshaw)</hi> from the time whereof, the memory of Man is not to the contrary; there was had, and hath been a Common Council of the same City from time to time, as of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten as need required Assembled in the same City, consisting of the Mayor and Aldermen of the said City for the time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and of certain Citizens be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Freemen of the said City not exceeding the number of two hundred and fifty persons out of the Citizens and Freemen of the City aforesaid, yearly Elected to be of the said Common Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil, which said Citizens so Elect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in such Common Council are called Commons of the City of <hi>London.</hi> And that within the City aforesaid (to wit, at the said Parish of St. <hi>Michael Bassieshaw,</hi> in the Ward of <hi>Bassie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shaw</hi> aforesaid) there is, and from the time whereof the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of man is not to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, there was such a Custom used and approved (to wit) that the Mayor and Aldermen of the said City, and such Citizens so Elected to be of the Common
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:95896:4"/>Council of the same City for the time being in, their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Council Assembled within the same City from the whole time aforesaid, according to the Custom of the City aforesaid, have made and constituted, and have been accustomed, and might, and can make and constitute Laws and Ordinances for the better Regulation and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the publick Markets within the City aforesaid; and for the appointing convenient Places and Times when and where within the same City the said Markets should be held; and for the assessing and reducing to certainty the reasonable Tolls, Rates, or Sums of Money to be paid by persons coming to the said Markets for Stalls, Stand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and other Accommodations by them had for the exposing to Sale Victuals and Provisions in those Markets, as often as, and when to them should seem expedient, yet so as such Laws and Ordinances be useful to our Lord the King and his People, and consonant to good Faith and Reason, and not contrary to the Laws and Statutes of this Realm of <hi>England;</hi> And that in the great Charter of the Liberties of <hi>England</hi> made and provided in the Parliament of Lord <hi>Henry</hi> the Third, sometime King of <hi>England,</hi> held at <hi>Westminster</hi> in the County of <hi>Middlesex,</hi> in the Ninth year of his Reign it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained. That the City of <hi>London</hi> have all its Antient Liberties, and its Customs; And the same Mayor and Commonalty, and Citizens of the City of <hi>London,</hi> do further say, That Lord <hi>Edward</hi> the Third sometime King of <hi>England</hi> in his Parliament held at <hi>Westminster</hi>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:95896:5"/>in the County of <hi>Middlesex,</hi> in the first year of his Reign by his Charter with the Assent of the Prelates, Earls, Barons, and whole Commonalty of his Realm in his said Parliament Assembled at <hi>Westminster</hi> aforesaid, and by Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the same Parliament did confirm to the then Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens of the City of <hi>London</hi> afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said, the Liberties following (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst other things) to hold to them and their Successors for ever, first reciting. That where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as in the great Charter of the Liberties of <hi>England,</hi> it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, that the City of <hi>London</hi> have all its Antient Liberties, and its Customs, and that the same Citizens at the time of the making of the said great Charter, and in the times of Saint <hi>Edward</hi> the King, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessor, and <hi>William</hi> the Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, and other the Progeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of the said King <hi>Edward</hi> the Third had divers Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Customs as well by the Charters of those his Progenitors, as without Charters of Antient Custom. The same King <hi>Edward</hi> the Third did will and grant for him and his Heirs by that Charter, by the Authority afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said, that the same Citizens should have their Liberties ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Form of the great Charter aforesaid, as by the said Charter bearing Date at <hi>West<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minster</hi> aforesaid, the sixth of <hi>March,</hi> in the aforesaid first year of the Reign of the said King <hi>Edward</hi> the Third, under his great Seal of <hi>England,</hi> produced here in Court doth more fully appear. And the same Mayor, and Commonalty, and Citizens of the City of <hi>London</hi> further say, That at the Instance and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:95896:5"/>Request of the Commonalty of the Kingdom of <hi>England</hi> Assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled in the Parliament of Lord <hi>Richard</hi> the Second, since the Conquest, late King of <hi>England</hi> held at <hi>Westminster</hi> aforesaid in the Seventh year of his Reign, for the cherishing of grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Quiet and Peace amongst the Leige People of the same late King, and for the Publick good, All the Customs, Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, Priviledges and Franchises of the City aforesaid, were rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied and confirmed to the then Citizens of the City aforesaid, and their Successors, by Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the same Parliament: And that our aforesaid Lord the now King, by his Letters Patents un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his great Seal of <hi>England,</hi> bearing Date at <hi>Westminster</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foresaid the four and twentieth day of <hi>June,</hi> in the fifteenth year of his Reign, which the same Mayor and Commonalty, and Citizens of the City of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> produce here in Court, for himself, his Heirs and Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessors did ratifie and confirm to the Mayor and Commonal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and Citizens of the City of <hi>London,</hi> and their Succes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sors, all, and every the Juris<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions, Authorities, Priviledges, Liberties, Franchises, Acquittan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Immunities and Customs whatsoever, which the said Mayor and Commonalty, and Citizens of the City of <hi>London,</hi> or their Predecessors, by the name of Mayor, and Commonalty, and Citizens of the City of <hi>London,</hi> or by the name of Mayor, Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermen, Citizens and Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty of <hi>London,</hi> or by the name of Mayor and Citizens of the City of <hi>London,</hi> or by the name of Mayor and Commonalty of the City of <hi>London,</hi> or by the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:95896:6"/>name of the Citizens of the City of <hi>London,</hi> or by the name of the Barons of <hi>London,</hi> or by the name of the Barons of the City of <hi>London,</hi> or by any other name whatsoever, by reason or vertue of the Letters Patents, Charters, or Confirmations in the same Letters Patents of our said Lord the now King before mentioned, or of any Usage or Usages, Prescription or Prescrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, or any other lawful means whatsoever in any time or times thentofore had, or reasonably used or exercised, To have, hold, enjoy and exercise all and singu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar the Premises aforesaid, to the same Mayor, and Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty, and Citizens of the City of <hi>London</hi> aforesaid, and their Successors for ever so fully, free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and entirely, and in as ample manner and form as in the same Letters Patents they are above mentioned to be given or granted, or otherwise by Usage, Prescrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or other lawful means or right whatsoever thentofore re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spectively were had, obtained, or enjoyed, as if they were, and had been, severally, particularly, and by name in and by the said Letters Patents of our said Lord the now King expressed, named, declared, granted and manifested, as by the same Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters Patents (amongst other things) more fully appeareth. And the same Mayor and Commonalty, and Citizens of the City of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> further say, that after that great Conslagration of the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test part of the City aforesaid, which was in the Month of <hi>September,</hi> in the year of our Lord, One thousand six hundred sixty six, and the Alterations in the City and Markets aforesaid, thereby occasioned, divers Contro
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:95896:6"/>versies and Questions did arise within the same City of, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the settling the Markets, &amp; the Sums of Money payable by the Liege people of our Lord the King, for Victuals and Provisions in those Markets exposed to Sale: And thereupon on the said <hi>Thursday</hi> the 17th day of <hi>Septem,</hi> in the 26th year of the Reign of our said Lord the now King aforesaid, Sir <hi>William Hooker</hi> Knight, then Mayor of the City aforesaid, and the Aldermen of the said City, and the Commons or Citizens of the Common Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of the same City then being in their Common Council then As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembled within the same City, (to wit, in the said Chamber of the <hi>Guildhall</hi> of the same City scituate in the said Parish of St. <hi>Michael Bas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sieshaw,</hi> in the Ward of <hi>Bassieshaw</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foresaid) according to the Custom of the said City, &amp; by the Authority of the same Common Council did make, constitute &amp; publish an Act or Ordinance for the better Regulation and Government of the publick Markets held within the City a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foresaid, entituled, (<hi>An Act for the settlement and well ordering the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral publick Markets within the City of</hi> London). By which said Act or Ordinance (amongst other things) reciting, That whereas for accommodation of Market people with Stalls, Boards, Shelter, &amp; other like things necessary for their Stand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in any of the Market places within that City, &amp; for cleansing, pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, scouring, and keeping clean the same; &amp; also for the defraying the incident charges of repairing and maintaining the said Markets; and likewise to gratifie and reward the care and aftendance of such per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons as should be imployed therein, there have alwaies been paid certain reasonable Rates for the said ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodations &amp; charges. And to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:95896:7"/>the intent that the said Rates may be ascertained and made publick to all Market people, whereby the persons that shall from thenceforth by Order of that Court of Common Council, be imployed as Collectors or Receivers of the same Rates, may be prevented from demanding, exacting, or receiving more than was allowed by that Act or Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance; It was ordered &amp; enacted by Authority of the same Com. Council, amongst other things, that all and every person &amp; persons re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sorting to any of the said Markets, to sell &amp; vend their commodities, shall from thenceforth pay unto such person or persons as were, or should from time to time be appointed to take and receive the profits of all, or any of the said Markets to the use of the said Mayor, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monalty, and Citizens of the City of <hi>London,</hi> of, and from all Market people thereunto resorting for their Stalls, Standings, and other Accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations in the several Market pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces as aforesaid, after the Rates fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, and no more (that is to say) for every Stall or Standing eight foot long, and four foot broad, for sale of Flesh-meat, or Fish, two shillings and six pence <hi>per</hi> week, for every Stall or Standing of six foot long, and four foot broad, two shillings <hi>per</hi> week, for every Stall or Standing of 6 or 8 foot long, and four foot broad for other commodities three pence <hi>per</hi> day, for every horse-load of provisions not upon Stalls, or under publick shelter, two pence <hi>per</hi> day, for every Dosser of like provisions, one penny <hi>per</hi> day, for every Cart-load with not above 3 horses, four pence <hi>per</hi> day; for every Cart-load with 4 horses, or above, 6 pence <hi>per</hi> day. And it was further or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered &amp; enacted by the Authority above<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said, That the Collectors or Receivers ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed as aforesaid, should have power up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on obstinate denial or delay of any of the Market people to pay the respective Rates abovesaid, them from their respective standings &amp; places to amove &amp; displace.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:95896:7"/>And the said Mayor and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monalty and Citizens of the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>London</hi> farther say, that the same rates by that Act or Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance as aforesaid, ordered to be paid at the said time of the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king that Ordinance, and from thenceforth hitherto were reasona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and yet are reasonable; and that the Rates and Summes of Money by the same Act or Ordinance or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered to be paid, are all the Rates, Tolls, and Summes of Money pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, and paid for Victuals and Provisions in the Markets afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said sold or exposed to Sale by any persons, from the said time of the making of the same Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance hitherto, to the use of the Mayor and Commonalty and Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens of the City of <hi>London;</hi> which said Rates so ordered to be paid, and no others, the same Mayor and Commonalty and Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens of the City of <hi>London,</hi> from the time of that Act or Ordinance as aforesaid made, hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto, have demanded and recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved according to the form and effect of the same Act or Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, which said Act or Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance is the same Law, by them the Mayor and Commonalty and Citizens of the City of <hi>London,</hi> above in Fact supposed to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted, specified in the said Plea of the said Attorney General a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove by replying Pleaded with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out that, That any Law, Act or Ordinance for Leavying the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney aforesaid, of Persons resort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Markets aforesaid, with Victuals and Provision; there to be sold, was enacted or made otherwise, or in any other man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, than the same Mayor and Commonalty and Citizens of the City of <hi>London</hi> have above al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged, as the same Attorney Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral for our said Lord the now King above supposeth: and this
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:95896:8"/>they are ready to verisy; and as to the residue of the aforesaid Plea of the aforesaid Attorney General, in assigning the Forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures as aforesaid, above by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying Pleaded, the same Mayor and Commonalty and Citizens of the City of <hi>London</hi> say, that on the sour and twentieth day of <hi>April,</hi> in the thirtieth year of the Reign of our said Lord the now King, and for divers years then last past, and since the same four and twentieth day of <hi>April,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in this Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> and elsewhere, (to wit, at <hi>London</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foresaid, in the said Parish of St. <hi>Michael Bassishaw,</hi> in the Ward of <hi>Bassishaw</hi> aforesaid,) there hath been contrived and carried on by the Papists, a traiterous and execrable Conspiracy and Plot, to Kill and Murder our Lord the now King, and to alter, change and subvert the ancient Government and Laws of the same Kingdom, and to suppress the true Religion esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blished in the same, and to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirpate and destroy the Professors of the same Religion; which said Plot and Conspiracy was contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and carried on in divers pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and by several wayes and means, and by a great number of Persons of several qualities and degrees, who acted and employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed themselves therein to execute and accomplish the aforesaid wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and traiterous designs and purposes; and that afterwards, (to wit) on the seven and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth day of <hi>September,</hi> in the thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth year abovesaid, Sir <hi>Edmond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury Godfrey</hi> Knight, then one of the Justices of our Lord the King, assigned to keep the Peace in the County of <hi>Middlesex,</hi> according to the Duty of his Office and Oath, at the Parish of St. <hi>Martins in the Fields,</hi> in the same County of <hi>Middlesex,</hi> did take Examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:95896:8"/>and Informations of the said Plot and Conspiracy, and Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation that that great Conslagra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the greatest part of the City of <hi>London,</hi> which was in the Month of <hi>September,</hi> in the year of our Lord one thousand six hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred sixty six, was done by the Papists; and afterwards by the Advice, Consent, Counsel, Insti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation and Procurement of some of the said Conspirators, divers Persons lay in wait and pursued the said Sir <hi>Edmondbury Godfrey</hi> divers dayes, with intent to Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him, (to wit) at the Parish of St. <hi>Mary le Savoy,</hi> in the said County of <hi>Middlesex,</hi> which said Murder afterwards, (to wit) on the twelfth day of <hi>October,</hi> in the thirtieth year aforesaid, at the same Parish by them was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petrated and effected, and was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petrated and done with intent to suppress the Examinations and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formations which he as aforesaid had taken, and to deterre and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage Magistrates and others from acting in the further Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of the Plot and Conspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spiracy aforesaid, for which said Murder <hi>Robert Green, Girald</hi> Clerk, <hi>Henry Bury, Lawrence Hill, Dominick Kelley,</hi> and <hi>Fillibert Vernat,</hi> afterwards, (to wit) in the Term of St. <hi>Hillary,</hi> in the thirtieth and one and thirtieth years of the reign of our said Lord the now King, in the Court of our Lord the King, before the King himself, at <hi>Westminster,</hi> in the County of <hi>Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dlesex,</hi> by a certain Jury of the same County of <hi>Middlesex,</hi> in due form of Law were Indicted, to which said Indictment afterwards, (to wit) the same Term, the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said <hi>Robert Green, Henry Bury,</hi> and <hi>Lawrence Hill,</hi> severally did Plead that they were not guilty thereof, and thereof put themselves upon the Countrey, and afterwards
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:95896:9"/>(to wit) the same Term of St. <hi>Hil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lary,</hi> in the same Court at <hi>Westmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster</hi> aforesaid, for the said Felony and Murther, by that Jury of the Countrey, in due form of Law were Tryed, and thereof lawfully Convicted and Attainted, as by the Record thereof in the same Court of our Lord the King, before the King himself at <hi>Westminster</hi> afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said remaining, more fully appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth; and that for the high Treasons, and traiterous Plots and Conspira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies aforesaid, <hi>Edward Coleman</hi> and <hi>William Ireland, Thomas Pickering</hi> and <hi>John Grove,</hi> and <hi>Thomas White</hi> alias <hi>Whitebread, William Harcourt</hi> alias <hi>Harrison, John Fenwick, John Gavan</hi> and <hi>Anthony Turner,</hi> and <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard Langhorn</hi> Esquire, being Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pists, and professing the Romish Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perstition, before the said thirteenth day of <hi>January,</hi> in the two and thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth year abovesaid, in due man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and according to the form of the Law of this Realm of <hi>England,</hi> were tryed, convicted &amp; attainted, (to wit) the aforesaid <hi>Edw. Coleman</hi> in the Term of St. <hi>Michael,</hi> in the 30<seg rend="sup">th</seg> year of the Reign of our Lord the now King, in the Court of our Lord the King, before the King him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self, (the same Court then, and yet being at <hi>Westminster</hi> in the County of <hi>Middlesex</hi>) as by the Record and Process thereof in the same Court remaining more fully appeareth: and the said <hi>William Ireland, Thomas Pickering,</hi> and <hi>John Grove,</hi> at the Gaole-delivery of our Lord the King at <hi>Newgate,</hi> held for the said County of <hi>Middlesex,</hi> at the <hi>Justice-Hall</hi> in the <hi>Old Baily,</hi> in the Suburbs of the said City of <hi>London,</hi> in the Month of <hi>Decenther,</hi> in the thirtieth year a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bovesaid, as by the Record and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cess thereof, in the Custody of the <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>es Rot<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>orum</hi> of the said County of <hi>Midil.</hi> remaining more fully ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth: and the said <hi>Thomas White</hi> al. <hi>Whit<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>bread, John Fenwick, William
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:95896:9"/>Harcourt</hi> alias <hi>Harrison, Johan Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>van,</hi> and <hi>Anthony Turner</hi> at the Goal delivery of our Lord the King, of <hi>Newgate,</hi> held by adjournment for the County of <hi>Middlesex</hi> aforesaid, at the aforesaid Justice Hall in the <hi>Old Baily,</hi> in the Suburbs of the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>London,</hi> on <hi>Friday</hi> the thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth day of <hi>June</hi> in the one and thirtieth year of the Reign of our said Lord, the now King as (by the Record and Process thereof in the Custody of the said <hi>Custos Rotulo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum</hi> of the same County of <hi>Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dlesex</hi> remaining more fully appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, and the said <hi>Richard Langhorn</hi> at the Goal delivery of our Lord the King, of <hi>Newgate,</hi> held by ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jourment for the said City of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> at Justice Hall in the <hi>Old Baily</hi> in the Parish of St. <hi>Sepulchre</hi>'s in the Ward of <hi>Farringdon</hi> without <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> on <hi>Saturday</hi> the fourteenth day of <hi>June</hi> in the one and thirtieth year abovesaid, as by the Record and process thereof in the Custody of the <hi>Costos Rotulorum</hi> of the said City of <hi>London,</hi> remaining more ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appeareth. And that <hi>William</hi> Earl of <hi>Powis, William</hi> Viscount <hi>Stafford, Henry</hi> Lord <hi>Arundel</hi> of <hi>Wardor, William</hi> Lord <hi>Petre,</hi> and <hi>John</hi> Lord <hi>Bellasis,</hi> the thirtieth day of <hi>November,</hi> in the thirtieth year of the Reign of our said Lord the now King, abovesaid, at <hi>Westmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster</hi> aforesaid in the said County of <hi>Middlesex,</hi> of the High Treasons, and Traiterous Plots, and Conspira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies aforesaid, were lawfully accus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and thereupon to the Prison of our Lord the King (to wit) to the <hi>Tower</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> were committed there safely to be kept, and being so in Custody, the said <hi>William</hi> Earl of <hi>Powis, William</hi> Viscount <hi>Stafford, Henry</hi> Lord <hi>Arundel</hi> of <hi>Wardor, Will.</hi> Lord <hi>Petre,</hi> and <hi>John</hi> Lord <hi>Bellasis</hi> at the Parliament of our said Lord
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:95896:10"/>the now King held at <hi>Westminster</hi> aforesaid the sixth day of <hi>March</hi> in the one and thirtieth year of his Reign by the Commons of this Reaim of <hi>England</hi> in the same Parliament Assembled before the Nobles and Peers of the same Realm, in that Parliament called together and As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembled; for that for many years then last past, there was contrived and carried on by the Papists a Trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous and execrable Conspiracy and Plot within this Kingdom of <hi>England</hi> and other places, to alter, change, and subvert the Ancient Government and Laws of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Nation, and to suppress the true Religion therein establish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and to extirpate and destroy the Professors thereof: Which said Plot and Conspiracy was contrived and carried on in divers places, and by several waies and means, and by a great number of persons of several qualities and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees who acted therein and inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded thereby to excute and accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plish the aforesaid wicked and Trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous designes and purposes. And that <hi>William</hi> Earl of <hi>Powis, Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant</hi> Viscount <hi>Stafford, Henry</hi> Lord <hi>Arundel</hi> of <hi>Wardor, William</hi> Lord <hi>Petre,</hi> and <hi>John</hi> Lord <hi>Bellasis,</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with <hi>Philip Howard,</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly called Cardinal of <hi>Norsolk, Thomas White</hi> alias <hi>Whitebread,</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly called Provincial of the Jesuits in <hi>England, Richard Strange</hi> lately called Provincial of the Jesuits in <hi>England, Vincent,</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly called Provincial of the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minicans in <hi>England, James Corker</hi> commonly called President of the Bonedictines, Sir <hi>John Warner</hi> alias <hi>Clare</hi> Baronet, <hi>William Harcourt, John Keins, Nicholas Blundel,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pool, Edward Mico, Thomas Bedingfeild</hi> alias <hi>Benefield, Basil Langworth, Charles Peters, Richard
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:95896:10"/>Peters, John Conyers,</hi> Sir <hi>George Wakeman, Thomas Fenwick, Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minick Kelly, Fitz-Gerald Evers,</hi> Sir <hi>Thomas Prest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, William Lovel</hi> Jesuits, Lord <hi>Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temore, John Carrel, John Townely, Richard Langhorne, William Fogarty, Thomas Penny, Matthew Medbourne, Edward Coleman, William Ireland, John Grove, Thomas Pickering, John Smith,</hi> and divers other Jesuits, Priests, Fryers, and other persons, as false Traytors to our Lord the now King, and this Kingdom with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the time aforesaid had Traiter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously consulted, contrived, and act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to and for the accomplishing of the said wicked, pernicious, and Trayterous designes, and for that end had most wickedly and Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terously agreed, conspired and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solved to Imprison, depose, and Murder his Sacred Majesty, and to deprive him of this Royal State, Crown, and Dignity, and by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious and advised speaking, wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and otherwise declared such their purposes and intentions. And also to subject this Kingdom and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the Pope, and to his Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannical Government, and to seize and share amongst themselves the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>states and Inheritances of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesties Protestant Subjects. And to erect and restore Abbies, Mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steries, and other Convents and Societies, which have been long since by the Laws of this Kingdom suppressed for their Superstition and Idolatry, and to deliver up and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>store to them the Lands and Pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sessions now vested in our now Lord the King and his Subjects, by the Laws and Statutes of this Realm, and also to found and erect new Monasteries and Convents, and to remove and deprive all Protestant Bishops and other Ecclesiastical per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons from their Offices, Benefices
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:95896:11"/>and Preferments, and by this means to destroy his Majesties person, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirpate the Protestant Religion, overthwart the Rights, Liberties, and Properties of all his Majesties good Subjects, subvert the lawful Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of this Kingdom and sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject the same to the Tyranny of the See of <hi>Rome.</hi> And that the said Conspirators, and their Complices, and Confederates, Traiterously had and held several Meetings, Assemb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, and Consultations, wherein it was contrived and designed among them what means should be used and what persons and Instruments should be employed to Murder his Majesty. And did then and there resolve to effect it by Poysoning, Shooting, Stabbing, or some such like way and means, and offered rewards and promises of advantage to several persons to Execute the same, and hired and imployed seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral wicked persons to go to <hi>Windsor,</hi> and other places where our Lord the King did reside, to Murther and Destroy his Majesty, which said persons or some of them accepted such rewards, and undertook the perpetrating thereof, and did actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally go to the said places for that end and purpose. And that the said Conspirators the better to compass their Traiterous designs, had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sulted to raise, and had procured and raised Men, Money, Horses, Arms, and Ammunition, and also had made application to, and treated and corresponded with the Pope, his Cardinals, Nuncioes, and Agents, and with other Foreign Ministers, and persons to raise and obtain supplies of Men, Money, Arms, and Ammu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition, therewith to make, levy and raise War, Rebellion, and Tumults, within this Kingdom, and to invade the same with Foreign forces, and to surprize, seize, and destroy his
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:95896:11"/>Majesties Navy, Forts, Magazines' and places of Strength within this Kingdom, whereupon the Calamities of War, Murders of innocent Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, Men, Women and Children, burnings, rapines, devastations, and other dreeadful miseries and mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs must have inevitably ensued to the ruine and destruction of this Nation. And that the said Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spirators had procured and accepted and delivered out several instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Commissions, and Powers made and granted by or under the Pope or other unlawful and usurp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Authority to raise and dispose of Men, Monies, Armes, and other things necessary for their wicked and Trayterous designes; and name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a Commission for the said <hi>Henry</hi> Lord <hi>Arundel</hi> of <hi>Wardor,</hi> to be Lord Chancellour of <hi>England,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Commission to the said <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam</hi> Earl of <hi>Powis</hi> to be Lord Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surer of <hi>England,</hi> another Commis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion to the said <hi>John</hi> Lord <hi>Bellasis</hi> to be General of the Army to be raised, another Commission to the said <hi>William</hi> Lord <hi>Petre</hi> to be Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant General of the said Army, and a Power for the said <hi>William</hi> Viscount <hi>Stafford</hi> to be Pay-Master of the Army: And that in order to encourage themselves in prose<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting their said wicked Plots, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spiracies and Treasons, and to hide and hinder the discovery of the same, and to secure themselves from Justice and punishment, the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spirators aforesaid, their Complices and Confederates had used many wicked and diabolical practises (to wit) they had caused their Priests to administer to the said Conspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratours an Oath of secrecy, together with their Sacrament and also had caused their said Priests upon Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessions to give their absolutions
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:95896:12"/>upon condition that they should conceal the said Conspiracy: And when about the month of <hi>September</hi> then last past Sir <hi>Edmundbury God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frey</hi> a Justice of the Peace, had ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Duty of his Oath and Office taken several examinations and informations concerning the said Conspiracy and Plot, the said Conspirators or some of them, by advice, assent, Counsel, and instiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the rest, did incite and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure divers persons to lie in wait and pursue the said Sir <hi>Edmondbury Godfrey</hi> divers days, with intent to murder him, which at last was perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trated and effected by them (for which said horrid Crimes and Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences, <hi>Robert Green, Henry Berry,</hi> and <hi>Lawrence Hill,</hi> had since been attainted, and <hi>Domonick Kelly,</hi> and <hi>Gerald,</hi> and others were fled for the same) after which Murder, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the body was found, or the Murther known to any but the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plices therein, the said persons falsly gave out, that he was alive and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately married, and after the body found, dispersed a false and malicious Report, that he had Murdered him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self. Which said Murther was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted with design to stifle and sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>press the Evidence he had taken, and had knowledge of, and discourage and deter Magistrates and others, from acting in further discovery of the Conspiracy and Plot, for which end also the said Sir <hi>Edmondbury Godfrey,</hi> while he was alive, was by them their complices and favourers threatned and discouraged (in his proceedings about the same) And that of their further malice they had wickedly contrived by many false suggestions to lay the imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and guilt of the aforesaid hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid and detestable Crimes upon the Protestants, that (so thereby they
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:95896:12"/>might escape the punishments which they had justly deserved and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose the Protestants to great scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal and subject them to Persecution and oppression in all Kingdoms and Countrys, where the Romish Relingion was received and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessed. And that all those Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, Crimes, and Offences above<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned, were contrived, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, perpetrated, acted, and done, by the said <hi>William</hi> Earl of <hi>Rowis, William</hi> Viscount <hi>Stafford, William</hi> Lord <hi>Petre, Henry</hi> Lord <hi>Arundel</hi> of <hi>Warder,</hi> and <hi>John</hi> Lord <hi>Bellasis,</hi> and other the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spirators aforesaid, against our So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign Lord the King, his Crown and Dignity, and against the Laws and Statutes of this Kingdom) ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Law and Custom of Parliament were impeached, and therewith duly charged, and in Prison for that reason were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, as by the Record and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cess thereof, remaining among the Records of Parliament more ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appeareth. And the same Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor, and Commonalty, and Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens of the City of <hi>London,</hi> fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther say, that in the Session of the aforesaid Parliament of our said Lord the now King held by Prorogation at <hi>Westminster</hi> afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said, upon the aforesaid one and twentieth day of <hi>October,</hi> in the two and thirtieth year of the Reign of our said Lord the now King abovesaid, in the replicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on aforesaid mentioned at the beginning of the same Session our Lord the now King out of his most Princely great care and ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nestness for the preservation of the Protestant Religion and his Subjects from the eminent dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers of Popish Conspiracies by his gracious Speech to both Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:95896:13"/>of the same Parliament, then and there made and spoken, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst other things did recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend to the Lords and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons in that Parliament assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled to pursue the further ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination of the Plot aforesaid, with a strict and impartial enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and to them he then said that he thought not himself nor them safe until that matter were gone through with. And therefore that it was necessary, that the said Lords in the prison of the <hi>Tower</hi> of <hi>London</hi> should be brought to their speedy Tryal, that Justice might be done. And the same Major, and Commonalty, and Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens of the City of <hi>London,</hi> fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther say, that afterwards in the same Session of Parliament, both Houses of that Parliament in prosecution of the said directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of our Lord the King did make a strict and impartial en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry concerning the said Plot, and upon that enquiry did de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare that there had been an hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible Plot and Conspiracy by the Papists against the person of our said Lord the now King, and his Government, which did then continue; And the Commons in the same Parliament assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled further declared, that that Plot and Conspiracy was sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported and carried on by po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent and restless practices and Machinations; especially during the late recesses of Parliament, and afterwards in the same Ses<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of Parliament, the Lords Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual and Temporal, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons in the same Parliament as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembled at <hi>Westminster</hi> aforesaid did make and exhibit to our same Lord the King their
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:95896:13"/>humble Address in form following, (to wit) That they His Majesties most Dutiful and Loyal Subjects, the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and Commons in that present Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament assembled, being deeply sensible of the sad and calamitous Condition of this Realm, occasio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned chiefly by the impious and horrid Conspiracies of a Popish Party, who have not only plotted and intended the Destruction of His Majesties Royal Person, but the total Subversion of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment and true Religion in this Kingdom of <hi>England</hi> established; and finding the same detestable Machinations still obstinately pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secuted by them, as well by fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting Divisions amongst His Majesties Loyal Protestant Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, as all other the most wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked Contrivances, notwithstand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the many Discoveries thereof by Gods great Mercy and wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Providence then lately brought to light: all which dreadful Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments then were impending over this Realm, for their many and grievous Sins, most deservedly, and could not otherwise in Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Reason be prevented, but by the particular Blessing of God up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Consultations and Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours of the Great Council of Him our Lord the King, then in Parliament assembled, did in all Humility beseech His Majesty, that by His Royal Proclamation a Day might be solemnly set apart wherein both they themselves, and all His Majesties Loyal Subjects, might by Fasting and Prayer en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour a Reconciliation with Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God, and with humble and penitent Hearts implore him by his Power and Goodness to divert these Judgments, and defeat the wicked Counsels and Devices of their Enemies, to unite the Hearts
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:95896:14"/>of the Loyal Protestant Subjects of our said Lord the King, and to continue his Mercy and the Light of his Gospel to our said Lord the King, and His said Subjects, and their Posterities, and more espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially to bestow his abundant Bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sings on His Sacred Majesty, and the then present Parliament, that their Consultations and Endeavours might produce Honour. Safety, and Prosperity to His Majesty and His People. And thereupon our said Lord the now King, during the said Session of Parliament, (to wit) on the second day of <hi>Decem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> in the abovesaid Two and thirtieth Year of His Reign, by His Royal Proclamation under His Great Seal of <hi>England,</hi> bearing date at <hi>Westminster</hi> the same Day and Year, reciting, That whereas the Lords Spiritual and Temporal and Commons in that Parliament assembled, by their Address to Him our said Lord the King, had made known unto Him, that they were deeply sensible of the sad and cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitous Condition of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, occasioned by the impious and horrid Conspiracies of a Popish Party, who had not only plotted and intended the Destruction of his Royal Person, but the total Subversion of the Government and true Religion established a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst the King Himself and His Subjects; And that the same dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stable Machinations were then ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinately prosecuted by them, as well by somenting Divisions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst His Loyal Protestant Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, as all other the most wicked Contrivances, notwithstanding the many Discoveries thereof by Gods great Mercy and wonderful Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence lately brought to light; All which dreadful Judgments were then impending over Him the same our Lord the King, and His
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:95896:14"/>said Subjects, for their many and grievous Sins, most deservedly, and could not otherwise in Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Reason be prevented but by the particular Blessing of God up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Consultations and Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours of His the said King's Great Council then in Parliament assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled; did most humbly beseech Him the same King, that a Day might most solemnly be set apart, wherein the King Himself, and all His Loyal Subjects, might by Fast<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Prayer endeavour a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation with Almighty God, and with humble and penitent Hearts implore him by his Power and Goodness to divert those Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and defeat the wicked Counsels and Devices of the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of Him our Lord the King and His said Subjects, to unite the Hearts of our said Lord the King's Loyal Protestant Subjects, and to continue his Mercy and the Light of his Gospel to our said Lord the King, and His said Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, and their Posterities; and more especially to bestow his abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant Blessings upon Him our Lord the King, and the then present Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, that their Constiltations and Endeavours might produce Honour, Safety, and Prosperity to our said Lord the King, and to His People: The same our Lord the King to that their humble Request most readily inclined, and did by that His Royal Proclamation com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand a General and Publick Fast to be kept throughout this whole Kingdom, in such manner as after by the same Proclamation was di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected and prescribed, that so both our same Lord the King and his People might send up their Prayers and Supplications to Almighty God to and for the Purposes aforesaid. And to the end that so Religious an Exercise might be performed at
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:95896:15"/>one and the same time, our said Lord the King, by that Proclamati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, did publish and delare to all his Loving Subjects, and did straitly charge and command, That on <hi>Wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesday</hi> being the Two and twentieth day of <hi>December</hi> then Instant that Fast should be Religiously kept and celebrated throughout His King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>England,</hi> Dominion of <hi>Wales,</hi> and Town of <hi>Berwick upon Tweed.</hi> And that the same might be perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with all Decency and Unifor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, the same our Lord the King, by the Advice of His Reverend Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops, did direct to be Composed, Printed, and Published such a Form of Divine Service as he thought fit to be used in all Churches and Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces at the Time aforesaid, and did give in Charge to His Bishops to disperse the same accordingly. All which our said Lord the King, by His Proclamation aforesaid, did ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presly charge, and command should be reverently and decently obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by all his Loving Subjects, as they tendred the Favour of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God, and would avoid His Wrath and Indignation against this Land, and upon pain of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergoing such Punishments as our said Lord the King could justly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict upon all such as should con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temn or neglect so Religious a Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; as by the Inrolment of the same Proclamation in the Court of <hi>Chancery</hi> of Him our Lord the King, remaining on Record, more fully appeareth. Which said Day of Fasting, according to the form &amp; effect of the Proclamation aforesaid, was duely and solemnly observed and celebrated in and through this whole Realm of <hi>England,</hi> and espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially at <hi>London</hi> aforesaid, in the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish and Ward aforesaid. And that in the same Session of Parliament last mentioned, the Commons of this Realm in the same Parliament
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:95896:15"/>assembled made a resolution to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to the Tryal of the said Lords, then being in the Prison of the <hi>Tower</hi> of <hi>London</hi> so as aforesaid impeached, and forthwith to begin with the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foresaid <hi>Viscount-Stafford,</hi> &amp; then gave noticethereof to the Lords of that Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, &amp; requested them to apoint a convenient day for the Tryal of the said <hi>Viscount-Stafford.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the said <hi>Viscount-Stafford</hi> of the High Treasons and Traiterous Plots and Conspiracies aforesaid, whereof he as aforesaid was impeached, by the Lords Temporal in the same Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment convened at the Prosecution of the Commons of this <hi>Realm,</hi> in that Parliament, Assembled in the same Session of Parliament was tried, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victed, and in due form of Law at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainted as by the Record and Process thereof, remaining among the records of Parliament more fully appeareth. And afterwards in the same Session of Parliament, Sir <hi>W<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lliam Scrogs</hi> Knight then Chief Justice of our Lord the King assigned to hold Pleas before the King himself, by the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of this <hi>Realm</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> in the same Parliament Assembled before the Nobles and Peers of this <hi>Realm</hi> in that Parliament called together and Convened according to Law and Custom of Parliament, was accused, and impeached of High Treason and other great Crimes, and Misdemea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors amongst other things, that he the said Sir <hi>William Scrogs,</hi> and then being Chief Justice of the Court of <hi>Kings-Bench,</hi> had Traiterously and wickedly endeavoured to subvert the Fundamental Laws and the Establisht Religion, and Government of this Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> and instead thereof to introduce Popery, and an Arbitrary and Tirannical Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, against Law, which he had declared by divers Traiterous and wicked Words, Opinions, Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Practises and Actions, and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:95896:16"/>also that whereas there had been an Horrid Damnable Plot, continued and carried on by the Papists, for the Murthering the King, the Subvertion of the Laws and Government of this Kingdom and for the Destruction of the Protestant Religion in the same, all which the said Sir <hi>William Scrogs</hi> well knew, having himself not only Tryed but given Judgment against several of the Offenders, nevertheless the said Sir. <hi>William Scrogs</hi> did at di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers times and places, as well sitting in Court as otherwise, openly defame and scandalize several of the Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses, who had proved the said Treasons against divers of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spirators, and had given Evidence against divers other persons, who were then untryed, and did endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to disparage their Evidence, and take off their credit whereby as much as in him lay, he had Traite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rously, and wickedly suppressed and stifled the discovery of the said Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pish-Plot, and encouraged the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spirators (to proceed in the same) to the great and apparent danger of his Majesties Sacred Life and of the well Established Government, and Religion of this Realm of <hi>England,</hi> as by the Record thereof among the Records of Parliament remaining more fully appeareth. And also in the same Session of Parliament, the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons in the same Parliament Assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, did declare that they were sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied, that there then was, and for divers years then last had been an Horrible and Traiterous Plot, and Conspiracy contrived and carried on by those of the Popish Religion in in the Kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> for Mas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sacreing the English, and the Subver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Protestant Religion, and the Ancient Established Government of that Kingdom; of which said Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible and Traiterous Plot and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spiracy. <hi>Richard Power</hi> Earl of <hi>Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rone,</hi>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:95896:16"/>in the Kingdom of <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> at the same Session of Parliament, by the Commons of this Realm of <hi>England</hi> in the same Parliament, Assembled before the Nobles and Peers of the same Kingdom of <hi>England</hi> in that Parliament called toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and convened, according to the Law and custom of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament was impeached and therewith duely charged and to the Prison of our Lord the King of the <hi>Gate-House Westminster,</hi> upon that occasion was committed as by the Record thereof among the Records of Parliament remaining more fully appeareth; and that as well the Lords as Commons in the said Parliament Assembled, in the same Session of Parliament were preparing Bills according to the custom of Parliament to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted into Laws, for the preserva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our Lord the now King, and his Protestant Subjects a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst Traterous Plots, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spiracies aforesaid tending, which said several Impeachments against the same <hi>Richard Power,</hi> and the said Sir <hi>William Scrogs,</hi> and the aforesaid <hi>William</hi> Earl of <hi>Powis, Henry</hi> Lord <hi>Arundel</hi> of <hi>Wardour, William</hi> Lord <hi>Petre,</hi> and <hi>John</hi> Lord <hi>Bellasis</hi> undetermined, and the same <hi>William</hi> Earl of <hi>Powis, Henry</hi> Lord <hi>Arundel</hi> of <hi>Wardour, William</hi> Lord <hi>Petre, John</hi> Lord <hi>Bellasis,</hi> and <hi>Richard Power</hi> in the Prison of our Lord the King, for the Causes afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said, as aforesaid being, the same Parliament upon the aforesaid tenth day of <hi>January,</hi> in the above<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said two and Thirtieth Year of the Raign of our said Lord the now King, was Prorogued as the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said Attorney General of our said Lord the now King, hath above thereof alledged without any Try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al of the said <hi>William</hi> Earl of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:95896:17"/>
                  <hi>Powis, Henry</hi> Lord <hi>Arundel</hi> of <hi>Wardour, William</hi> Lord <hi>Petre, John</hi> Lord <hi>Bellasis,</hi> Sir <hi>William Scrogs</hi> and <hi>Richard Power,</hi> or any of them of the High Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons and other the Premises whereof, they respectively as aforesaid were Impeached (and who otherwise then in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment could not thereof be Try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) made or had, and be fore such Bills were enacted into Laws, which said Speech of our Lord the King, and the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarations and Proceedings of the Lords and Commons of that Parliament, during the said Session of the same Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament as aforesaid, made be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Prorogation of that Parliament were published (to-VVit) at <hi>London</hi> aforesaid, in the said Parish of St. <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chael Bassieshaw</hi> in the Ward aforesaid; by reason of which said Premisses, the Citizens and Inhabitants of the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said City of <hi>London,</hi> being faithful Subjects of our said Lord the now <hi>King,</hi> were greatly affright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de and affected in their minds, and very much Disquieted with the deep Sence and Apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of the great dangers im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending and hanging over the person of our Lord the now King and his Government of this Realm and the Protestant Religion: and the Professors of the same by Reason of the Conspiracies aforesaid, not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise (as by the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, in the said Parliament Assembled, in their Addresses aforesaid, Published by our Lord - the King in the said Proclamation as aforesaid is affirmed) in hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man reason to be prevented then
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:95896:17"/>than by the particular Blessing of God upon the Consultation and Endeavours of the same <hi>Parliament:</hi> certain <hi>Citizens,</hi> and <hi>Inhabitants</hi> of the same <hi>City,</hi> in the name of the <hi>Citizens,</hi> and <hi>Inhabitants</hi> of the said <hi>City,</hi> before the Petition specifyed in the aforesaid Plea of the said At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torny General above, by Replying, Pleaded, made, or ordered to be made (to wit) on the aforesaid <hi>Thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth</hi> day of <hi>January,</hi> in the above<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said <hi>two</hi> and <hi>thirtyeth</hi> year of the Reign of our said Lord the now King, did exhibit to Sir <hi>Patience Ward</hi> Knight, then Mayor of the <hi>City</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> and the Aldermen of the said <hi>City,</hi> and the <hi>Commoners</hi> or <hi>Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens</hi> of the Common-Council of the same <hi>City</hi> then Assembled, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Custome of the said <hi>City</hi> in the aforesaid Chamber of the <hi>Guild-Hall</hi> of the same <hi>City,</hi> in the Parish of St. <hi>Michael Bassieshawe</hi> aforesaid, a certain Petition, contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, That they, the <hi>Citizens</hi> &amp; <hi>Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants</hi> of the <hi>City</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> being deeply sensible of the Evils and Mischeifs hanging over this <hi>Nation</hi> in general, and this <hi>City</hi> of <hi>London</hi> in particular, in respect of the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of the Kings Person, the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant Religion, and His well Esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blished Government, by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued hellish and damnable De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signes of the <hi>Papists</hi> and others, their adherents; and knowing no way (under Heaven) so effectual to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve His Royal Majesty, &amp; the said <hi>Citizens,</hi> and <hi>Inhabitants,</hi> from the utter ruine and destruction, threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, as by the speedy sitting of the then present <hi>Parliament</hi> (the Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prising Prorogation of which great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly added to and increased the just Fears and Jealousies of the minds of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:95896:18"/>said Petitioners; They the said Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners did beseech the same Common-Councel so as aforesaid assembled, to acquaint his Majesty with those their Fears and Apprehensions, and that it was the humble and earnest desire as well of them the Petitioners as them the Magistratis. Aldermen, and Commons of that Common-Councel, That His Majesty would be pleased for the utter defeating the wicked and bloody Purposes of their Enemies, to permit the then present <hi>Parliament,</hi> which stood Prorogued to the <hi>Twentyeth</hi> day of the then instant <hi>January,</hi> then to Assemble and continue to Sit un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till they should have effectually secured this Kingdom against <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery,</hi> and redressed the manifold Greivances, under which, it then groaned; And that for their im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate security, that the same Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrates, and Aldermen, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of that Common-Councel, would order whatsoever else should be thought necessary, and expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to them (in that time of emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent danger) for the Safety of that great <hi>City:</hi> And because by the Law of the Land of this Kingdom of <hi>England</hi> it is lawful for the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of our Lord the King, in their straits and difficulties, humbly to to Petition our Lord the King for suitable remedy in that behalfe to be had; on the said <hi>Thursday</hi> the <hi>Thirteenth</hi> day of <hi>January</hi> in the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bovesaid <hi>Two</hi> and <hi>Thirtyeth</hi> year of the Reign of our said Lord, the now King, the said Sir <hi>Patience Ward,</hi> Knight, then Mayor of the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said <hi>City</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> and the Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of the same <hi>City</hi> (to wit) Sir <hi>Thomas Aleyn</hi> Knight and Barro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net, Sir <hi>John Predericke</hi> Knight,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:95896:18"/>Sir <hi>John Lawrence</hi> Knight, Sir <hi>George Waterman</hi> Knight, Sir <hi>Joseph Shel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> Knight, Sir <hi>James Edwards</hi> Knight, Sir <hi>Robert Clayton</hi> Knight, Sir <hi>John Moore</hi> Knight, Sir <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Pritchard,</hi> Knight, Sir <hi>Henry Tulse,</hi> Knight, Sir <hi>James Smith</hi> Knight, Sir <hi>Robert Jeffery</hi> Knight, Sir <hi>John Shorter</hi> Knight, Sir <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Gould</hi> Knight, Sir <hi>William Raw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterne</hi> Knight, Sir <hi>Thomas Beckford</hi> Knight, Sir <hi>John Chapmen</hi> Knight, Sir <hi>Simon Lewis</hi> Knight, <hi>Thomas Pilkington</hi> Esq; and <hi>Henry Cornish</hi> Esq; and the Commons or <hi>Citizens</hi> of the Common Council of the said <hi>City,</hi> then Assembled in their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Council, according to the cus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome of the said <hi>City,</hi> within the same <hi>City</hi> (to wit) in the said Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the <hi>Guild-Hall</hi> of that <hi>City,</hi> out of Hearts truely Loyal to our Lord the King; and for the satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of the <hi>Citizens,</hi> and <hi>Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants</hi> of the same <hi>City,</hi> who had ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited the Petition to them in forme aforesaid, for the alleviating their fear and apprehension, and inquietude, and with intent (as much as in them was) for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servation of the Person of our Lord the now King, and his Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this Realme of <hi>England</hi> and the Protestant Religion, did give their Votes and suffrages, and <hi>(Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nime Contradicente)</hi> did agree and order, That a certain Petition un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the name of them, the Mayor, Aldermen and Commons of the <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> of <hi>London</hi> Assembled in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Council unto our said Lord the now King should be exhibited: The tenor of which Petition follows in these <hi>English</hi> words; to wit, <hi>To the Kings Most Excellent Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty,</hi> The <hi>Humble</hi> Petition of the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:95896:19"/>Lord Mayor, Aldermen &amp; Commons of the <hi>City</hi> of <hi>London</hi> in Common-Council Assembled, most humbly sheweth, That Your Majestyes <hi>Great</hi> Council, in <hi>Parliament,</hi> have<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in their late Session, <hi>in Pursu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of Your Majestyes direction,</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred upon a <hi>Strict</hi> and <hi>Impartial</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry into the horrid and execra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Popish</hi> Plot which hath been for Several years last past, and still is <hi>Carried</hi> on for <hi>Destruction</hi> of Your <hi>Majestyes</hi> Sacred Person and <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernement,</hi> and <hi>Extirpation</hi> of the Protestant Religion, and the utter ruine of your Majestyes Protestant Subjects; and haveing so far pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded therein, as justly to attaint upon full Evidence one of the five Lords Impeached for the same, and were in further Prosecution of the remaining four Lords, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Conspirators therein: And as well the Lords Spiritual and Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral, as the Commons in your said <hi>Parliament</hi> Assembled, haveing de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared, That they are fully satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed that there now is, and for di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verse years last past, hath been an horrid and treasonable Plot, and Conspiracy contrived, and carried on by those of the Popish Religion in <hi>Ireland,</hi> for Massacring the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish,</hi> and subverting the Protestant Religion, and the Ancient Establish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Government of that Kingdom. And your said Commons haveing Impeached the Earl of <hi>Tyrone,</hi> in order to the bringing him to justice for the same; and haveing under examination other conspirators in the said <hi>Irish</hi> Plot; And your said Commons having likewise Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peached Sir <hi>William Scroggs,</hi> Chief Justice of Your MAJESTIES Court of <hi>Kings Bench</hi> for Treason,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:95896:19"/>and other great Crimes and Misde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meanors, in endeavouring to subvert the Laws of this Kingdom by his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrary and Illegal Proceedings, and having voted Impeachments against several other Judges for the like Mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demeanors, your Petitioners cousider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the continual hazards to which your sacred Life, and the Protestant Religion, and the Peace of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom are exposed, while the hopes of a Popish Successor gives Countenance and Encouragement to the Conspira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors in their wicked Designs. And considering also the disquiet and dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Apprehensions of your good Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, by reason of the Miseries and Mischiefs which threaten them on all parts, as well from Foreign Powers, as from the Conspiracies within your several Kingdoms, against which no sufficient remedy can be provided but by your Majesty; and your Parliament were extreamly surprised at the late Prorogation, whereby the prosecution of the publick Justice of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and the making the Provisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons necessary for the preservation of your Majesty and your Protestant Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects hath received an interruption. And they are the more affected here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, by reason of the Experience they have had of the great Progress which the emboldned Conspirators have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly made in their Designs, during the late frequent recesses of Parliament; but that which supports them against Despair, is, the hopes they derive from your Majesties Goodness, that your intention was, and does conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue by this Prorogation, to make way for your better concurrence with the Counsels of your Parliament. And your Petitioners humbly hope that your Majesty will not take offence that your Subjects are thus zealous, and even impatient of the least delay of the long hoped for Security, whilst they see your precious Life invaded, the true Religion undermined, their Families and innocent Posterity likely to be subjected to Blood, Consusion and Ruine, and all these dangers en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creased, by reason of the late Endeavours of your Majesty and your Parliament, which have added Provocation
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:95896:20"/>to the Conspirators, but have had little or no effect towards the securing against them, and they trust your Majesty will graciously accept this Discovery, and desire of their Loyal Hearts to preserve your Majesty, and whatever else is dear to them, and to strengthen your Majesty against all Popish and pernicious Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sels, which any ill affected persons may presume to offer: They do therefore most humbly pray, that your Majesty will be graciously pleased (as the only means to quiet the minds, and extinguish the fears of your Protestant People, and prevent the eminent dangers which threaten your Majesties Kingdoms, and particularly this your great City, which hath already so deeply suffered for the same) to permit your said Parliament to sit from the day to which they are Prorogued, until by their Counsels and Endeavours, those good remedies shall be provided, and those just ends attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, upon which the safety of your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesties Person, the preservation of the Protestant Religion, the Peace and Set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlement of your Kingdoms, and the welfare of this your ancient City, do so absolutely depend for the pursuing and obtaining of which good effects, your Petitioners unanimously do offer their Lives and Estates. And shall ever pray, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And they did then and there further agree and order, That that Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition after the presentation thereof to our same Lord the King should be Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by such person as the said then Maior of the City of <hi>London</hi> aforesaid should appoint. Which said Petition was so ordered to be Printed, with intent that the publishing of false Rumors and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports of and concerning the Petition exhibited to our said Lord the King might be prevented; the Enemies of our Lord the King, and the Conspira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors aforesaid, from proceeding in their Conspiracy aforesaid might be deterred, the perturbations which the good and Loyal Subjects of our said Lord the now King, for the causes aforesaid, had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived in their minds, might be allevia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and the Citizens and Inhabitants of the same City might better know what had been done in the said Common-Council concerning the matter contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Petition aforesaid to the same
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:95896:20"/>Common-Council as aforesaid exhibited. And that the aforesaid Petition to our said Lord the King, so agreed to be presented, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards (to wit) the aforesaid thirteenth day of <hi>January,</hi> in the two and thirtieth year, abovesaid, to our same Lord the King most humbly was presented, (to wit, at <hi>London</hi> aforesaid, in the aforesaid Parish of Saint <hi>Michael Bassieshawe,</hi> in the Ward aforesaid) and afterwards (to wit) on the fifteenth day of the same Moneth of <hi>January,</hi> by <hi>Samuel Roycroft</hi> (whom the said Sir <hi>Patience Ward,</hi> then Mayor of the City of <hi>London</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to had appointed) was Printed according to the Order aforesaid, in that behalf made (to wit) at <hi>London</hi> aforesaid, in the Parish and Ward aforesaid. Which said Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and the Printing thereof in the form and for the cause aforesaid done, are the same Petition, and the Printing and Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lishing thereof specified in the aforesaid Plea of the aforesaid Attorney General above, by replying pleaded—Without that, That any Petition of or concerning the Prorogation of the Parliament aforesaid, was made, Ordered, Published or Printed otherwise, or in other manner than the same Mayor and Commonalty and Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens of the City of <hi>London</hi> have above al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged, as the same Attorney General for our said Lord the King above supposeth. And this likewise they are ready to veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie: Whereupon the same Mayor and Commonalty and Citizens of the City of <hi>London,</hi> do not intend that they, by any things before alledged, have forfeited the aforesaid Liberty, Priviledge and Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chise, to be of themselves one Body Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porate and Politick, in deed, fact and name, by the name of the Mayor and Commonalty and Citizens of the City of <hi>London,</hi> and by the same name to plead and be impleaded, to answer and be answered unto by them above, as aforesaid claimed; And as before pray Judgment, and that that Liberty, Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge and Franchise to them and their Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessors for ever, for the future, be allowed and adjudged, and that they as to those Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>misses, be dismissed from this Court, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>